<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The famine of the word threat[e]ned to Israel, and Gods call to weeping and to mourning being two sermons preached on the fast day, Novemb. 13, 1678, and on the fast day, April 11, 1679 / by James Brome ...</title>
            <author>Brome, James, d. 1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18967</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12219656</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12219656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56367</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56367)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 129:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The famine of the word threat[e]ned to Israel, and Gods call to weeping and to mourning being two sermons preached on the fast day, Novemb. 13, 1678, and on the fast day, April 11, 1679 / by James Brome ...</title>
                  <author>Brome, James, d. 1719.</author>
                  <author>Brome, James, d. 1719. Gods call to weeping and to mourning.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 69 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Clark for Richard Chiswel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:56367:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guil. Sill, <hi>R. P. D.</hi> Hen. <hi>Epiſc.</hi> Lond. <hi>à ſacris domeſticis.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May. 26. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56367:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Famine of the Word</hi> Threatned to ISRAEL, AND GODS CALL <hi>To Weeping and to Mourning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING TWO SERMONS PREACHED On the Faſt Day, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 13. 1678. AND On the Faſt Day, <hi>April</hi> 11. 1679.</p>
            <p>By JAMES BROME, A.M. Rector of <hi>Cheriton</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Clark,</hi> for <hi>Richard Chiſwel,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56367:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56367:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>JAMES BROCKMAN,</hi> Eſq;, My moſt honoured Friend and Patron; And his Vertuous Conſort Madam <hi>LUCY BROCKMAN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THeſe Sermons finding ſo favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an acceptance at your hands, and being ſo generally deſired and called for by all the neighbourhood, I thought it my duty to proſtrate them both at your feet, and uſher them out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to light under your moſt auſpicious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage.</p>
            <p>Theſe perillous Times into which we are fallen, as they call for a ſerious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation on all ſides, ſo do they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand our joint-endeavours to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it; and if I can be any way inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to this good work in the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Papers; as it is the utmoſt of
<pb facs="tcp:56367:3"/>my deſign, ſo likewiſe of my deſire; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be further to give hereby a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my real gratitude for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold favours ſo frequently conferred, ſince I had the honour to be under your wings, upon</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged Servant <hi>James Brome.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56367:3"/>
            <head>The Famine of the Word <hi>Threatned to ISRAEL,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">SERMON I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>AMOS viij. Verſ. 11, 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, the days come, ſaith the Lord God, that I will ſend a Famine in the Land; not a Famine of Bread, nor thirſt for Water, but Hearing the Words of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>And they ſhall wander from Sea to Sea, and from the North, even to the Eaſt, they ſhall ran to and fro to ſeek the Word of the Lord, and ſhall not find it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT was ever an act of great mercy and kindneſs in the God of Heaven and Earth, that he never iſſued out his Judgments in the World, but he gave time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notice of them before their approaches, to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mens Conſciences, either by timely Repentance to divert them, or elſe by Vigilancy and Prayer to prepare againſt them.</p>
            <p>I might give you ſundry inſtances that this is the certain method of Gods proceeding with mankind. Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he deſtroyed the Old World, and waſhed away their pollutions by the general Innundation, <hi>Noah,</hi> the <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56367:4"/>of Righteouſneſs,</hi> was the Harbinger of that news, and he forewarned them what would follow their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual diſobedience, and perſeverance in Iniquity. After the ſame manner did he deal with <hi>Sodom,</hi> with <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and with <hi>Niniveh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I need look ſo far back; <hi>Iſrael</hi> a people of Gods own chooſing, had ſufficient experience of his loving kindneſs, and patience, and forbearance in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Though that Generation of men were a ſort of people ſo refractory and ſtubborn, ſo ſtiff-necked and diſobedient, ſo unſufferably wicked, and ſuch notorious tranſgreſſours, that God might in juſtice have ſwept them away with the <hi>Beeſom of Deſtruction,</hi> without giving them the leaſt ſpace of time to conſider of their ways, or amend their doings; I ſay, though he might have opened all the treaſuries of his Vengeance, and ſent down his arrows in great numbers upon their heads by reaſon of their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold provocations againſt him; yet did he never do this, but firſt by his Prophets and Meſſengers for warned them of what would happen: he did not ſtrike till he dealt with them as the Angel did with <hi>Balaam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 22.31.</note> open their eyes that they might ſee the blow was coming; he did not proceed to ſentence till he had firſt convicted them, and repreſented their guilt in a true Mirrour before them; he did not make them examples of his Juſtice, till he had firſt declared what it was had provoked him, and what ſuch wilful provocations did deſerve at his hands: thus did God ſtill temper his Mercy with his Juſtice, forewarn them, that they might be fore-armed. And for this very end and purpoſe was this precaution which God gave <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the words read unto you, <hi>Behold, the days come, ſaith the Lord God, that I will ſend a Famine in the Land, not a Famine of Bread, nor a Thirſt of Water, but Hearing the Words of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From which words I ſhall diſcourſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Nature of that Judgment which is here
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56367:4"/>threatned to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhew you the dreadfulneſs of it. It is a Famine, but <hi>not of Bread, nor of Thirſt for Water, but Hearing the Words of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall conſider the reaſon of this denunciation, what was the ground and original of it; and what it was that cauſed God Almighty to threaten that people with ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere a Judgment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall endeavour to ſhew how they might, and we may prevent the like Judgment, which ſeems at this time to hang over our heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I begin with the firſt of theſe, the Nature of that Judgment which is here threatned to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 'tis <hi>Famine.</hi> A ſore Judgment indeed, the very name of which is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently dreadful and terrible, were it but onely a corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhment. For if by Famine the Prophet had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant ſcarcity of Bread, or extream want of Victuals,
<note place="margin">Gen. 43.1.</note> ſuch a Famine as hapned in <hi>Canaan</hi> in the Patriarch <hi>Jacobs</hi> days; or ſuch a Famine as fell upon <hi>Samaria</hi> in the days of <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 6.25.</note> when an Aſſes head was ſold for fourſcore pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſilver, and the fourth part of a Kab of Doves dung for five pieces of ſilver, that indeed would have been a ſore evil, by the fearful effects that would have followed and enſued upon it. For to ſee men and women fainting for lack of Bread, and ready to prey upon and devour each other, to hear their Children and Sucklings,
<note place="margin">Lament. 2.11, 12.</note> rending the Skies with their bitter ejulations, and crying to their Mothers, Where is Corn and Wine? whileſt their ſouls were ready to be poured forth in their Mothers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom; nay, to behold women eating the fruit of their own wombs,
<note place="margin">2 Kings 6.28.</note> and children become a feaſt to their Mothers that newly bore them, as it hath hapned many times through the extremity of hunger; this muſt needs be a very dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful calamity which would grieve the heart, and afflict the eyes of all ſuch as did behold it.</p>
            <p>And yet this corporal Famine, though to us it appears to be the greateſt of Evils, is nothing to that Famine which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56367:5"/>is here threatned to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which was the <hi>Famine of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Words of the Lord,</hi> or the ſcarcity and want of Heavenly Bread, by depriving them of all holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Duties. For certainly this is meant, when God threatens to ſend a Famine amongſt them, that is, utterly to ſubvert the whole Jewiſh Church and Religion, to baniſh them from his Temple, and all their legal ſacrifices, to deprive them of all their Rites, and Ceremonies, and Sacraments, which were moſt dear and pretious to them, take from them the Law, with which before he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted them, and to divorce and ſeparate them from their Prieſts and their Prophets, who were the true and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Expounders of it. All this is implied by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the Word. And ſo the Judgment will appear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be very dreadful and terrible, upon theſe three accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe all entercourſe and communion was likely to be cut off betwixt God and them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe by this means they would be reduced to a very deplorable condition, in relation to their ſouls, by being deprived of all ſuch means as ſhould be moſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial and advantagious to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe this commonly being the laſt of Judgments, for God to deprive them totally of his worſhip, muſt needs be moſt fatal and pernicious to them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By this means all entercourſe and communion was likely to be cut off betwixt God and them. As it was the greateſt of honours to the Jewiſh Nation, that they were ſeparated from the reſt of the World as a People peculiar to God, to whom he was pleaſed very frequently to make greater manifeſtations of his love and favour than to any other community of mankind throughout the face of the Earth; ſo was it ſtill a further enhanſment of their glory, that God was pleaſed to chooſe their Metropolis <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> as his own City, and in that to accept of a Temple, where he took delight to be called upon and worſhiped,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56367:5"/>rather than elſewhere; for <hi>at Salem was his Tabernacle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 76.2.</note> 
               <hi>and his dwelling place in Sion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 122.4.</note> that Temple was his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion houſe and habitation, <hi>whither the Tribes went up, the Tribes of the Lord unto the teſtimony of Iſrael, to give thanks to the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now when once their provocations were grown ſo high, and their ſins and iniquities were riſen to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as to enforce him to abominate both them and their Temple, and make him loath and reject both them and their Religion, what farther hopes could they have of any favour, or of any entercourſe and communion betwixt God and them? In vain was it for them to expect that God ſhould any longer ſtrive to endear them by any former familiar ways of kindneſs, when he was reſolved to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don both them, and their Worſhip; and all their Incenſe, and their Sacrifices became very loathſome and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his ſight. For Religion being the Cement, the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the chief Bond of Union and Communion betwixt God and Man; when that is once broken, or diſſolved, farewel to Gods love, to his favour and friendſhip; no longer doth God regard any perſons than they are kept cloſe to him, by the firm ties of Duty and Obedience. And therefore in this reſpect a Judgment of this Nature to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh men from his Altars, to deprive them of his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and not to ſuffer them any longer to tread within his Courts; I ſay, ſuch a Judgment of Famine muſt needs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very terrible, becauſe when God rejects men as his Worſhippers, he rejects them likewiſe for being his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites; and no longer than they continue in his Church or in his ſervice, muſt they expect any communion or any friendſhip from him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly this Judgment was the more dreadful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by this means <hi>Iſrael</hi> was like to be reduced to a very deplorable condition in relation to their ſouls, by being deprived of all ſuch means as ſhould be moſt advantagious to them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56367:6"/>
            <p> As the Jews were happy in all manner of bleſſings, ſo were they in that great bleſſing which God was pleaſed to beſtow upon them, by ſending them his Meſſengers early and late to inſtruct them. Theſe perſons were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called <hi>Seers,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Prophets,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Prieſts,</hi> but all declared unto them the will of God, and expounded to them the Law and the Teſtimony: to theſe therefore the people had recourſe in all doubts, in all ſtraits, in all emergencies, and by them all their ſcruples were ſolved, and their ignorance diſpelled, and their duty plainly taught and reiterated to them.</p>
            <p>But now by this Famine they were like to loſe all theſe, God was reſolved to take away their Prophets from them, to ſuffer their Rabbies and Doctors of the Law no longer to inſtruct them: and then what do we think could follow, but a Night of Ignorance and Error? what could we expect from them, when theſe lights were put out, but that, like their Neighbours round about them, they ſhould all be invelop'd with the dark miſts of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatry?
<note place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> though their <hi>Prieſts lips did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve knowledge,</hi> yet if they were not permitted to ſeek it at their mouths, they muſt needs grow ſtupid and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<note place="margin">Titus 1.16.</note> fooliſh and extravagant, abominable and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and <hi>unto every good work reprobate,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fitleſs, and unfaſhionable.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, for they were not only like to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of thoſe perſons who expounded the Law, but of the Law it ſelf, with all its Worſhip and Sacrifices; and that ſtill enhanſeth further the grievouſneſs of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: not to have their Prieſts left amongſt them was a great loſs, but to be deprived of Gods Word too, was the greateſt Judgment could light upon them: for now their ſouls were like to periſh for want of food, Gods Word being nutriment to the Soul as Bread is to the Body; and that being ſubtracted and taken away from them which ſhould nouriſh them up unto eternal life, the means cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56367:6"/>the end could never be obtained; and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence the Soul was not onely like to ſtarve here, but to periſh hereafter too, and to lie down in woe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to all eternity. A ſad Judgment indeed! that God ſhould ſubtract from them all means whereby to render themſelves happy, that he ſhould ſnatch them from their Prieſts, rend them from his Altars, and by taking the light of his Word from them likewiſe, condemn them to a far greater than Egyptian darkneſs,; this ſtill renders it more grievous and dreadful.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But there is a third aggravation of it ſtill behind, That this is the laſt of Judgments which God uſually makes uſe of, when mens iniquities are ripe and ready for deſtruction, to deprive them of his true Worſhip, and to remove their Candleſtick out of his ſight.</p>
            <p>He that can calculate in how many inſtances Humane Nature is paſſive, may quickly make an eſtimate of <hi>Iſraels</hi> calamities, which were ſo manifold and terrible, that God Almighty might have ſeemed even to have emptied his Magazine of Judgments, and to have diſcharged them all upon the Jewiſh race. In all the Hiſtory of former Ages, and places, there is no where to be met withall any Generation of Mankind, with whom God had ſo many controverſies, and upon whom he did pour down his hotteſt fury and diſpleaſure dreſt up in ſuch various and diſmal ſhapes, as he did upon this ſtubborn and incorrigible people. There was not any manner of Judgment but the Jews were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with; and our Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> reckons up a whole Catalogue of ſufferings, which ſucceeded one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that rebellious Nation.
<note place="margin">Cap. 4. v. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> He tells us that God did not only cleanneſs of teeth in all their Cities, and want of Bread in all places, and with-held the rain from them, ſo that three Cities wandred to one City to drink water; but likewiſe that he ſmote them with blaſting and with mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew, with the Peſtilence after the manner of Egypt, with the Sword, and with Fire as diſmal as that which redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56367:7"/>
               <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> to a heap of rubbiſh and aſhes; and yet for all this they would not return unto God by reformation and amendment.</p>
            <p>And do we think it poſſible for Gods Spirit always to ſtrive with ſuch a froward Generation? was it not high time for God to uſe the laſt and moſt rigorous means, when all other proved uſeleſs and ineffectual? Was in not high time for God quite to caſhier them, and caſt them out of his ſight, when all other methods, though the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of the greateſt fury and ſeverity could no way reclaim them? No doubt it was: and therefore to this laſt of Judgments he threatens to have recourſe;
<note place="margin">V. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore this will I do unto thee, O Iſrael, and becauſe I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God O Iſrael;</hi> reſolving hereby, that becauſe nothing elſe would avail, to deſtroy their Nation, to root up that Vine and Vineyard which his own right hand had planted, to <hi>ſend a Famine in the Land, not a Famixe of bread, nor thirſt for Water, but of hearing the words of the Lord;</hi> by which they ſhould be reduced to ſo wretched and deplorable a condition, as to turn com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Vagrants or Vagabonds, and <hi>to wander from Sea to Sea, and from North to Eaſt, and to run to and fro to ſeek the Word of the Lord,</hi> and yet ſhould not be able after all their weariſom journies, after all their narrow ſearches and diſquiſitions to find that Word, that Law, thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which they ſought and hunted after.</p>
            <p>And thus I have acquainted you with the Nature of that Famine, and the dreadfulneſs of it, which is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> from whoſe example it will become a duty incumbent upon us, to look back upon our ſelves, whoſe ſtate and condition at this day ſeems not at all unlike to theirs then: for our ſins are of as deep a die, and our abominations as loathſome, and our tranſgreſſions as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, and our provocations as daring, and our impieties as provoking as theirs was before us, and God ſeems therefore now to threaten us after the ſame manner as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56367:7"/>he did the Jews, with as bad or worſe a Famine by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſuch hainous and abominable provocations.</p>
            <p>And that this is too great a truth, will plainly appear to any one that conſiders the preſent poſture and ſtate of affairs in this Kingdom; for are there not at this day a brood of ſanguinary, blood-thirſty, and wicked Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> who have endeavoured to ſubvert both Church and State, and reduce us all to a Famine indeed, to a real deſtitution of all true ſpiritual comforts and refreſhments? Had they not almoſt brought their wicked deſigns to effect, and doth not our Religion ſeem ſtill to lie at the ſtake? Doth not Deſtruction ſtill hover over our heads? And have we any certain ſecurity that we may not yet become a prey to theſe merclleſs Wolves and Tygers? There is more than a probability that God Almighty may ſuffer theſe very perſons to become ſnares and traps to us, ſcourges in our ſides, and thorns in our eyes.
<note place="margin">Joſh. 23.13.</note> 'Tis more than probable that thoſe who ſo induſtriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult our ruine, may yet attain to their end, and ſo we may all periſh through their malicious machinations, that our Religion may be undermined, our Churches violated, our Temples made the Neſts and Cages of Popiſh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatry, and we our ſelves fall a Sacrifice to the Pope and his devilliſh Emiſſaries. And if this ſhould come to paſs, which our ſins and manifold tranſgreſſions do juſtly deſerve and call for; Alas, into what unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable calamities ſhould we be involved? This would be a Famine of the higheſt degree, a Judgment the moſt grievous of all Judgments, as will appear again by theſe three following circumſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For firſt this would be a moſt certain indication, that as the meaſure of our iniquity was full, ſo the cup of Gods anger was full likewiſe, and that he was pouring out his utmoſt indignation againſt us. If once God ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our Church to fall, and our Religion to be taken from us; if he ſhould once remove our Candleſtick, and not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56367:8"/>permit us any longer enjoyment of his ſacred Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces amongſt us, we may be aſſured that his fury was kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled to the utmoſt height, that he ſuffered all this becauſe he could no longer endure us in his ſight, becauſe our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſervice was an abomination to him, and our worſhip being ſo extreamly tinctured and mixed with hypocriſie, did enforce him to draw away his face from us.</p>
            <p>For as true zeal and piety endear men to God, and render them his Favourites; ſo hypocriſie and irreligion eſtrangeth Gods affection utterly from them; nay, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a ſeparation, and ſets God at open enmity with them, and when once God hath declared himſelf an Enemy, then follow his Judgments, then are all the Vials of his Anger opened, and Sluces of his diſpleaſure plucked up to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm them; and theſe fruitleſs Fig-trees, theſe unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Servants, theſe wicked tranſgreſſors are curſed, and made an example of vengeance to terrifie others from the like evil courſes.</p>
            <p>So that if God ſhould deal thus with us, and puniſh us after ſo rigorous, and ſo ſevere a manner, I know not for my part what would become of us; there is no further hopes of favour, of kindneſs, of friendſhip from him, we might have improved theſe better to our advantages whileſt we enjoyed them;
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.43.</note> and if the Kingdom of God, <hi>i.e.</hi> the Goſpel of Chriſt be taken from us, it will be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſome other Nation to bring forth better fruits un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its enjoyment than we have done. So that this is the firſt thing that ſpeaks the dreadfulneſs of this Judgment, becauſe it will be a teſtimony, that God is irreconcilably angry with us, that he is reſolved to deſtroy us, and root out our memorial from off the face of the Earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, there is another thing which will ſpeak the dreadfulneſs of this Judgment, and that is, that it will not onely be a means to cut us off from all hopes of Gods love and favour for the preſent, but for the future too, by depriving us of all thoſe means which might be moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56367:8"/>to procure and regain it: for ſhould ſuch a Famine come amongſt us, then farewell to Gods Word and Miniſters, and by conſequence if theſe, which are the means and conduit-pipes of Grace, were ſtopped up, the way to Heaven would be precluded and ſtopped up like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Now that this would certainly be our caſe, ſhould Popery once more make a ſtep over the Seas, I ſhall evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to you in a few inſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For firſt, you would have ſome indeed come amongſt you, who would call themſelves the Miniſters of God, but you would quickly find a vaſt difference betwixt them and thoſe who now are his lawful Ambaſſadors; for they would not trouble themſelves to preach up the Goſpel ſo much as their own ſelves, their own gain, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and filthy lucre: and though 'tis the misfortune and a ſad fate which attends the preſent Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be accuſed as covetous perſons, or hirelings, proud, or imperious perſons, men who lord it over their Brethren, and who encroach too far upon the dues, and rights, and eſtates of the Laity, yet ſhould the Scene change, and theſe men be caſhiered, you would find, that what you accuſe them falſly of, would be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly verified in their Popiſh ſucceſſors; and you would learn by too woful experience, what it is to be Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridden, as you now call it, when upon every petty di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſte, upon the leaſt injurious uſage or affront put upon them, you ſhould hear them thundring forth, as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens did of old to the primitive Chriſtians, <hi>Chriſtiani ad Lecnes,</hi> Away with the Chriſtians to the Lions; ſo they to you, <hi>Haeretici ad Carbones,</hi> Away with theſe Hereticks to Fire and Faggot. Then would you value thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters whom you now deſpiſe, and he whom you are pleaſed now to eſteem the moſt contemptible man amongſt us, would then be thought worthy of your beſt words and elogies, when your backs once felt but the ſmart of the <hi>Romiſh Rod;</hi> and every Pariſh-Prieſt would be even
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56367:9"/>an Anti-Pope to command you at his beck, and aw you at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, As the Miniſtry would fail, ſo would all true Religion too; For in ſtead of Gods Ordinances, humane Inventions ſhould be enforced upon your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and Superſtition and Idolatry ſhould be impoſed upon you, under the ſpecious titles of Piety and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. You ſhould have Prayers indeed allowed you, but they ſhould be a Compound of <hi>Ave-Maries,</hi> and of Prayers to the Saints, and Prayers for the Dead; and that too in an unknown Tongue, and in a Language which none of you could poſſibly underſtand, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence could never ſay <hi>Amen</hi> at your Devotions. You ſhould have the Pſalter of the bleſſed Virgin, compiled by the Seraphical Doctor S. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> preſented to you as more uſeful than the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of holy <hi>David;</hi> and a Maſs-Book clapt into your hands; but your Bibles claſpt up and taken away from you, and you prohibited the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures upon the penalty perhaps of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation. And in ſtead of the pure and ſincere milk of the Word tendred you by ſome ſober and rational Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, you ſhall have probably one of <hi>Johannes Argentus</hi> his prime Catholick Diſciples come, and extol in the Pulpit the excellent qualities of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> Milk, or one of S. <hi>Francis</hi> his Fry, crying up the great Vertues of S. <hi>Francis</hi> his Slipper; or the healing faculties of S. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronica</hi>'s Handkerchief; or elſe from ſome other of thoſe Religious Juglers you ſhall hear a long ridiculous ſtory of ſome miraculous Saint out of their famous Legend, which ſhall be as fooliſh and incredible as the Fable of <hi>Garagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua,</hi> or the <hi>Wandring Jew.</hi> Nay beſides all this, you ſhall not only be compelled to worſhip the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and pray to Saints, and fall down before Images, and pay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to Reliques, and proſtrate your ſelves before Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and Crucifixes; but you ſhall be denied the Cup in the Sacrament, and taught that the Bread is the very
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56367:9"/>Body of Chriſt, and under that notion will be enforced to receive and pay it homage: I ſay, notwithſtanding after 'tis conſecrated by the Prieſt, you ſee, and feel, and taſte, and ſmell that it is ſtill Bread, notwithſtanding you know 'tis a plain contradiction for one and the ſelf-ſame Body to be in a hundred places at one and the ſame time; yet this you muſt believe, and a thouſand other ridiculous fanſies, as that the Pope is infallible, that he is Chriſts Vicar, the Univerſal and Supreme Paſtor of the Univerſe, and is endowed with a Power and Empire over all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings, Princes, and Potentates, at the leaſt <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia.</hi> Further, that there is ſuch a place as Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, that Confeſſion to the Prieſt is abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation, that in the Maſs there is a propitiatory Sacrifice both for quick and dead, that the Saints have a mint and treaſury of good works to ſpare, which they can lend to others, who want them, upon occaſion; that to doubt in the leaſt of miracles, traditions, and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, the power of the Pope, and his Prieſts, or to entertain the leaſt thought of the poſſibility of being ſaved in any other Religion is a moſt enormous crime; Theſe, and whatever elſe the Prieſt ſhall bid you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that you muſt believe without making any ſcruple, or asking any queſtions for conſcience ſake: What days they pleaſe to ſet apart you muſt be ſure to obſerve, what penances they inflict you muſt patiently undergo, what they think fit to command from you, you muſt undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly grant, or elſe nothing would make atonement for ſuch contempt and obſtinacy, but your very lives and fortunes.</p>
            <p>This would be your caſe and this your condition, ſhould Popery prevail; and would not this be a ſore judgment indeed to be deprived of your preſent honeſt and good Miniſtry, and to be enſlaved by Popiſh tyranny? to be robbed of Gods ſacred word and to give ear to fables? to leave the true Religion, and be made vaſſals to a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which is ſuperſtitious and idolatrous? In a word,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56367:10"/>
               <hi>to forſake the Fountain of living Waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>and to dig unto your ſelves Ciſterns, broken Ciſierns that will hold no Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi> How could you hope to find the way to Heaven by ſuch guides, to gain an entrance by ſuch blind Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to merit glory by ſuch an implicit Faith? Certainly in ſuch circumſtances men muſt needs run the greateſt hazards imaginable of their immortal Souls, there would be little or no hopes of Salvation under ſuch means, and therefore a Judgment of this nature muſt needs be very terrible and amazing, nay the greateſt of Judgments that could befall this Nation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Eſpecially if we confider in the third place, that when God ſends this, it is the laſt of all Judgments, and therefore muſt needs be the moſt pernitious and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: When God once works the downfal of a Nation, when he deſtroys a Kingdom, or ſuffers a Church to be buried in ruine, we may be ſure God hath poured upon that people the utmoſt dreggs of his fury, and that there is no other Judgment to ſucceed, but the moſt fatal of all is happened to them, in which all in general ſhall be concerned, and have their portion. In the caſe of the Sword, the Peſtilence, or Fire, 'tis poſſible ſome few may eſcape the Divine Vengeance, ſome may be reprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved till a further opportunity; but when once a whole Polity is laid in deſolation, every one then is a ſufferer, the blow is levelled at all, and there is none but feels the heavineſs, and the ſmart of it. And then woe, woe to us, ſhould this be our condition, as we have too great reaſon to fear it may be ſtill by Gods former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with us, and our incorrigibleneſs under all his methods which he hath made uſe of to reclaim us: we know, 'tis not many years ago, ſince the Sword did glut it ſelf with the blood of many thouſands of our native Inhabitants; after that the Plague came in triumph, and erected its Trophies over all our Kingdom; after this ſucceeded a dreadful and terrible Fire, which laid in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56367:10"/>aſhes the Metropolis of our Nation: And ſince all theſe three Judgments have not wrought in us that ſincere and hearty Reformation, which God expected they ſhould, what can we expect, but that God ſhould give a word of command for the laſt to come amongſt us, and ſo trouble himſelf no longer to puniſh ſo refractory and incorrigible a People? And if ſo, we can none of us eſcape, but we ſhall find the effect of it to be very direful and terrible; for when our Church is once in the duſt, and our Religion ſubverted, when all our Rites and Solemnities of Worſhip are obliterated and aboliſhed, and Gods Holy Word which ſhould nouriſh us up unto eternal Life, is taken from us, 'tis much to be feared, that God will never be ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled as to reſtore them to us again, ſeeing we mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them ſo ill, when we had the happineſs of enjoying them: nay though afterward when we perceive the want of them, we ſhould ſeek them carefully with tears, and wander from Sea to Sea, and from Eaſt to North to find them, yet ſhall we be unſucceſsful, and miſs of what we deſire; lie down we muſt in the ſhades of darkneſs, where the Sun of Righteouſneſs will no more ariſe upon us with healing under his wings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And now what it was that provoked God to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuch bitter and ſevere things againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and upon what particular grounds and reaſons we in this Nation may juſtly dread the ſame Judgment, is the next thing I am to give an account of: Where though <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as I might ſhew at large, was a people notorious for all manner of tranſgreſſions againſt the Law of God, for all manner of vices which could poſſibly be committed, ſo that God had juſt reaſon to complain of them by his Prophet <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>That even from the days of their Fathers they had gone away from his Ordinances, and had not kept them,</hi> upon which account God might juſtly execute the utmoſt rigor of his juſtice upon them; yet I ſhall at preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance but in three or four things, which as they did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56367:11"/>aggravate their guilt, ſo did they call for, and haſten the greateſt vengeance upon their heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For firſt, they were a ſort of people that mocked, and deſpiſed both Gods Word and Meſſengers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, they made no ſcruple to deprive their Prieſts of that, which was ſet apart by God as their Lot and Portion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, they were generally addicted to Irreligion and Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And fourthly, if they did not break forth into open profaneneſs, they were no leſs blameable for their baſe ſecret hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Now when I have drawn the parallel betwixt them and us, and have ſhewn you that we have equalled, if not out-vied them in all theſe things; we ſhall then find from our ſelves as great reaſon to fear that God ſhould pour down in this nature his utmoſt indignation upon us, as ever he did upon that wicked and obſtinate people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a ſort of people, that mocked, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed both Gods Word, and Meſſengers: He that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fults the Hiſtory of thoſe times, will find this very viſible in their manners, and practices; in the days of <hi>Amos</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> they were grown to that paſs, that they ſilenced their Prophets,
<note place="margin">Amos 2.12.</note> and commanded them not to ſpeak, unleſs it were ſuch things as tickled their ears,
<note place="margin">Iſaiah 30.10.</note> or gratified their humours; but when this would not do, and they found them of ſuch courage and undaunted ſpirits, that they did ſtill <hi>cry aloud, ſpare not, but lift up their voices like trumpets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 58.1.</note> 
               <hi>to ſhew Gods people their tranſgreſſion, and the houſe of Jacob their ſin;</hi> why then they began to convert all their Prophets ſerious diſcourſes into mirth, and drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and made ſport with the graveſt matters, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of Religion: they burleſqu'd the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi>'s words, and turned the expreſſions he uſed into <hi>ridicule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 23.33, 36.</note> crying in contempt, <hi>The burden of the Lord,</hi> which is called <hi>perverting the words of the Living God:</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56367:11"/>After the ſame manner did they deal with <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.32. <hi>In Canticum oris ſui vertun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Vul. Lat.</note> whoſe words they turned into pleaſant Songs, or as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of our Bibles have it, they made loves or jeſts of the moſt ſacred things, which the Prophet did utter for their benefit, and advantage: And no wonder that when <hi>the Fathers had eaten ſower Grapes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.2.</note> 
               <hi>the Childrens teeth were ſet on edge;</hi> no wonder that when the Fathers had attained to ſo good a knack of mocking their Prophets, and were ſo notorious for the obloquies and contempt which they paſſed upon them, that their Children did ſo readily follow their examples, and that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliſha</hi> could not poſſibly eſcape the virulency of their tongues, whoſe years, one would have thought, ſhould have rendred them uncapable of ſuch vile miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors; upon which account no doubt it was, that the little Children having ſucked in ſuch prejudices againſt the Prophets with their milk, and learnt to rail againſt them from their very cradles, ventured to clamour after that good man with ſuch vile and baſe language (though they paid for it very dearly with the loſs of their lives) when the beſt words they could afford him were no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than theſe, <hi>Go up thou baldhead, go up thou baldhead:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 2.23, 24.</note> In fine their own Chronicles have given us ſo full an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their ſcoffing, ſarcaſtick temper, that we need look no further for a teſtimony hereof, for 'tis ſaid there, that <hi>they mocked the meſſengers of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 30.1.</note> 
               <hi>and deſpiſed his words, and miſuſed his Prophets, until the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his People, till there was no remedy:</hi> from which it appears, that God did for ſome time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the people of <hi>Judah,</hi> beyond what they could have expected, waiting for their amendment until they added impudence to their obſtinacy, and made ſport with the Prophets, and laughed at every thing that was ſacred and religious; then the peremptory Decree came forth, and there was no hopes of eſcaping,
<note place="margin">Lament. 4.16.</note> then did <hi>the anger of the Lord divide them, and he did no more regard them, becauſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56367:12"/>they regarded not the perſons of the Prieſts, and favoured not the Elders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, as nothing doth more provoke God, than ſuch a ſcoffing humour, and ſuch a contemptuous uſage of his Servants, and Meſſengers; ſo nothing doth ſooner precipitate his Judgments, nay nothing can be a more certain prognoſtick, that they are even at the door, than that is: for there can be no worſe ſymptom to a people, than to laugh at the only means to cure them, and if this once grow common, it muſt needs make their condition deſperate; for then it comes to Gods turn to laugh, and to mock too; <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye have refuſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.24, 15, 26.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded, but ye have ſet at nought all my counſel, and would have none of my reproof, I alſo will laugh at your calamity, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k when your fear cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this was one reaſon, why God reſolved to ſend a Famine of the Word amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> to aboliſh their Worſhip, and baniſh them from their Prieſts, becauſe they made ſo light of them, nay did even take a pride to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, and contemn them, to vilifie and abuſe them, what can we expect leſs in this Nation, who have far ſurpaſſed that people in this ſcoffing vein? Search the Annals of all Hiſtory, and compare the manners of all the Nations of the Earth with ours, and you ſhall find this vice, no not even amongſt Turks and Heathens, ſo predominant as it is in ours: and he that conſiders the baſe and unjuſt accuſations, the vile and ignominious obloquies, the ſordid and unworthy aſperſions, the black and malitious calumnies, in a word, the general deſpite and contempt, that is thrown upon the preſent Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may cauſe him juſtly to believe, that God hath very great reaſon to revenge this injury by depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them of ſuch Paſtors, whom they uſe ſo deſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.11, 12.</note> and to <hi>ſend them ſtrong deluſions to believe a lie, that they might all be damned, who believed not the truth, but</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56367:12"/>had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs: I wiſh that this miſchief had not ſpread it ſelf ſo univerſally over the face of this Nation, but (alas) the diſeaſe is grown now ſo Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical, that the Prieſt affords matter of ſport for all companies, and he that can be ſo ingenious to have a fling at him, ſhall be cryed up for a man of great wit and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, though in other things he is looked upon as very mean and inconſiderable; nay, our Children too (like the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> I mentioned before) have drawn in theſe prejudices with their very breath, for a man can ſcarce walk the ſtreets in many places, but he ſhall hear ſome of them ſpeak ſomething contemptible of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, if he chance to paſs by; as if thoſe, who were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly reputed the glory of Chriſtendom, were now to be eſteemed the very refuſe of the people; nay, the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring, <hi>catharmata, &amp; ludibria,</hi> the laughing ſtocks, and the moſt hateful of all mankind.</p>
            <p>I remember, that it was part of the Liturgy in the <hi>Greek</hi> Church of old, to praiſe God, that out of his infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion he had given them Miniſters and Teachers, not only of the ſame nature, and infirmities with themſelves, but alſo of like guilt, and under the ſame condemnation; becauſe, thereby having in themſelves a ſenſe of their own infirmities, and knowing the burden of ſin, and the ſubtilty of Satan, they might the better know likewiſe how to offer up Sacrifices and Oblations, both in behalf of themſelves and the people: but how is the ſcene alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red! when inſtead of prayers, we meet with curſes, and the failings of ſome are either imputed to all, or elſe mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to ſo high a degree, as if we were the Peſts and Grievances of the Nation! And now if God look upon the diſhonour done to his Miniſters, as done to himſelf, if St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak true,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ iv. 8.</note> that they who deſpiſe them deſpiſe not men, but God; according to that uſual ſaying, <hi>Every mans meſſenger is as himſelf,</hi> I cannot ſee why God ſhould any longer ſuſpend his judgments from us, who ſtand
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56367:13"/>guilty before him of ſo foul a miſdemeanour: why ſhould he not deprive us of thoſe perſons whom we thus ſet at nought, and uſe ſo contumeliouſly? and it may be ſome of us would be glad if God ſhould do ſo; but ſhould this happen to us, I dare very confidently affirm, that we ſhould find it by too woful experience the greateſt curſe yet that ever befel this Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond reaſon, that might enforce God to haſten ſuch a judgment upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by rooting out their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, was their depriving the Prieſts of that Lot and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he himſelf had ſet apart for their uſe: whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knows any thing of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Oeconomy, cannot poſſibly be ignorant, that the <hi>Jews,</hi> by a more eſpecial injunction of God himſelf, were commanded to pay the tenth of all their ſubſtance to the Prieſts who ſerved at his Altars, which tithes God was pleaſed to call his own, and to ſanctifie himſelf, commanding that no part of it,
<note place="margin">Levit. xxvii. <hi>v.</hi> 30, 31.</note> whether it was good, or whether it was bad, ſhould be ſo much as changed by any of the people: now not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, ſo covetous and worldly minded were the generality of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to defraud God of his own, and the Prieſts of that which was allotted for their ſhare: and though, when God reproved them for their unjuſt and fraudulent deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings towards him, they did juſtifie themſelves, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate the caſe with him, and were ſo inſolent as to ask him the queſtion (notwithſtanding they could not but know their guilt) Wherein they had done him any inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? God deals very plainly, and tells them, that it was in robbing him of his Tithes and his Offerings: <hi>Will a man rob God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. iii. 8.</note> 
               <hi>yet ye have robbed me; but ye ſay, wherein have we robbed thee? in tithes and in offerings:</hi> Well, but what was the fatal conſequence of ſuch filthy defraudations? what did they get by their Rapine and their Sacriledge? the next verſe tells you, the curſe of God was their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<note place="margin">Verſe 9.</note> 
               <hi>Ye are curſed within curſe: for ye have robbed me,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56367:13"/>even this whole nation.</hi> And may not we juſtly dread the ſame curſe, whoſe defraudations are as great, and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg as inſufferable? for though there is a certain portion of tithes ſet apart for our preſent Miniſters under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which our pious and good Auceſtors have beſtowed upon the Church, and the Laws of our own Nation have ratified and confirm'd, and God himſelf under the Goſpel doth allow and commend, yet ſuch is the unſatiable ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of ſome worldlings amongſt us, that they make no conſcience to defraud the Miniſters of their due; nay, have the impudence, in their vulgar diſcourſe, to aſſert very commonly, that it is no ſin to cheat the Parſon; as if the taking away the Corn which belongs to me, were not as directly a breach of the eighth Commandment, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal,</hi> as the taking away a Horſe, which doth not belong to me, would be from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man: and now, when that which ought to be our ſhame is our Glory and our Triumph, when fraud and downright cozenage is ſo plauſibly ſwallowed down, and they who are guilty of ſuch things, yet lay their hands on their mouths, and ſay they are innocent,
<note place="margin">Jer. v. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Shall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord, ſhall not my ſoul be avenged of ſuch a nation is this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> complaint of old,
<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>Serm. de Temp.</hi> 219. <hi>Hom.</hi> 48.</note> that the covetous coldneſs of ſome Chriſtians in his time perſuading them to rob God, and to withdraw part of his portion, Tithes, from the Miniſters, was a grand preſage of Wars and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities coming upon them in <hi>Africa,</hi> (as indeed they did ſoon after) when the hand of violence would revenge the injury of Sacrilegious avarice, with the Soldiers Rapine, ſaith he, or the Exchequers confiſcation will take what was grudged for Chriſt and his Church: I pray God the ſame injurious uſage from the Laity, at this day, do not portend to this Nation the ſame, or worſe Calamities, that the <hi>Popiſh Harpies</hi> do not come in amongſt us, and revenge our injuries upon thoſe perſons who have dealt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56367:14"/>unjuſtly by us: I pray God (I ſay) that this ſin be not ſo far laid to their charge, as that ſome of that rapacious crue do not make as great a prey of them as they have done of us; for although it would be but a juſt one, yet it would be a curſe indeed, a puniſhment very grievous.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But I haſten to a third thing, which might preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate ſuch a judgment upon the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, and that was their unſufferable degeneracy into all manner of irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and profaneneſs: if ever God had any right and title to worſhip, and ſervice from any people, it was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly due from the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were ſo far his favourites, that he was pleaſed to entruſt and depoſit with them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle calls them, his Holy Oracles, the Divine Law written with his own finger; nay, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did manifeſt himſelf to be a God who highly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited their true and ſincere ſervice, by the manifold deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances he wrought for them, and the wonderful mercy he conferred daily upon their Nation: and yet ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, inſenſate and ſtupid a people was this, that they were ſo far from calling to mind thoſe ſignal favours, wherewith he endeavoured to oblige them, and from thoſe conſiderations return him, in lieu thereof, a juſt and due proportion of duty and obedience, that inſtead of that they were arrived at ſo great a height of boldneſs and impiety,
<note place="margin">Mal. i. 13.</note> as even to ſnuff at Gods ſervice, and grew weary of it, and thought it a burden and a grievance to them; and therefore upon their Sabbaths and Feſtival days, when they ſhould have paid God the moſt ſolemn and ſerious Devotion, they began to think thoſe days moſt irkſome and troubleſome, becauſe they ſeem'd to hinder their gain and their Merchandize, and had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to cry out,
<note place="margin">Amos viii. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>When will the new Moon be gone, that we may ſell corn, and the ſabbath, that we may ſet forth wheat, making the Ephah ſmall, and the Shekel great, and falſifying the ballances by deceit? That we may buy the poor for ſilver, and the needy for a pair of ſhooes; yea, and ſell
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56367:14"/>the refuſe of the wheat?</hi> nor did they ſtick here, but they became ſtill greater proficients in that helliſh art of irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for the Prophet tells us again that they profaned the name of the Lord, ſaying, <hi>The table of the Lord is polluted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. i. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and the fruit thereof, even his meat is contemptible:</hi> now upon theſe terms it was not poſſible for God any longer to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his hand, when he ſaw his Worſhip neglected, his Ordinances ſpurn'd at, and his Holy Name profaned: the next thing he could expect was to have his very Eſſence queſtioned, and his Soveraignty over them openly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned, and therefore it was high time for him to exert his power, and make them ſmart for their impieties.</p>
            <p>And if we be convicted; and found guilty of as evil courſes, we likewiſe can expect no leſs favour or mercy: Now that this is our caſe, the Atheiſm and Impiety of the preſent Age doth abundantly verifie, for men are not content to be modeſt Atheiſts, and to ſay ſecretly in their hearts, with the fool, that <hi>there is no God,</hi> but impiety appears with a brazen forehead, and diſputes its place in every company, and without any regard to the voice of nature, to the dictates of conſcience, and the common ſenſe of mankind: men peremptorily determine againſt a ſupream Being, account it a pleaſant divertiſement to droll upon Religion, and a piece of wit to plead for Atheiſm: nay, as though the fountain of the great deep was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up, and Hell were let looſe, and the Priſoners there had ſhaken off their Chains and came upon the earth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs and all manner of wickedneſs grow ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and barefaced, that men do not only reproach, but totally neglect all Religion and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>Indeed in former Ages it was for the honour and glory of the Engliſh Nation, that as their genius prompted them to be very devout and religious, ſo they never omitted any opportunity to ſhew that real love they had for the Worſhip of God, and how mightily they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in a continual veneration of his moſt Sacred
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56367:15"/>Perſon, and in a conſtant performance of all the holy Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which were enjoyned them by Chriſtianity: But ſince Atheiſm hath flown over the Seas, and infected this Kingdom; Good God! what a ſtrange degeneracy is in mens natures and inclinations? For if they do not openly diſcard all Religion, yet they have ſo ſmall a regard and eſteem for it, that it may juſtly provoke God to take it from them, and let them feel the want of it: When we ſee ſome ſo careleſs, and indifferent in performing all manner of religious Duties, that they care not whether they ſerve God, or not, when we ſee ſome abſenting themſelves from his Worſhip, and making every idle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe ſerve to cover their negligence, others abſenting themſelves from the Sacrament, and running away from the Lords Table with as much eagerneſs, as if the Plague would break forth upon them, and conſume them; others cavilling at the Liturgy, and Offices of the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not dreſſed up, nor ſhaped according to their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: in fine, when we ſee Gods Houſes deſerted, his Altars unfrequented, his Sacred Days profaned, his Word deſpiſed, and all manner of true Zeal and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion quite difcarded in our daily aſſemblies; ſhall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord? ſhall not my Soul be avenged of ſuch a Nation as this? I am ſure we have all the reaſon to expect he ſhould, when we give him ſuch juſt reaſon to avenge himſelf of us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Eſpecially if we conſider in the fourth place, that there is ſomething ſtill behind, which as it doth aggravate ours, and <hi>Iſraels</hi> guilt, ſo it will likewiſe haſten our pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as it did theirs before us; and that is Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, a ſin of ſo deep a dye, that nothing doth more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe God againſt a Nation than this doth: that no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could poſſibly be more addicted to this, than the <hi>Jews,</hi> is very evident from all their Prophets, they made nothing to commit the greateſt villanies in the world, and defile themſelves with the blackeſt crimes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56367:15"/>a ſpecious pretence of piety and innocency, cry out <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>the Temple of the Lord are theſe:</hi> They pretended great zeal and love for Gods Worſhip, and Sanctuary, and var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed over all their evil actions with the falſe colours of Sanctity, and Holineſs: But behold how God, who ſeeth through the thickeſt veils of Hypocriſie, the moſt ſecret imaginations of the ſons of men, reproves them for it: <hi>Will you ſteal, murder, and commit Adultery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>and ſwear falſly, and burn Incenſe unto</hi> Baal, <hi>and walk after other gods, whom ye know not, and come, and ſtand before me in the Houſe, which is called by my Name?</hi> As if God had ſaid, Do you think that though you are guilty of all theſe abominable ſins, yet your coming to my Houſe, your treading in my Courts, your calling on my Name, ſhall make an atonement for them? So far are ſuch dealings from pacifying my wrath, that it will but kindle it the more againſt you, for, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> 
               <hi>mine anger, and my fury ſhall be poured out upon this place, upon man and upon beaſt, and upon the trees of the field, and upon the fruit of the ground, and it ſhall burn, and not be quenched:</hi> And therefore no wonder again it is that you find him by his Prophets <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Amos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 1.11, 12 Amos 5.21.</note> rejecting all their Sacrifices, and Oblations, and Aſſemblies, and profeſſing that he hated all their New Moons, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Feaſts, and that all their Worſhip was an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to him, when he found it ſo extremely mixed with Hypocriſie; for when men pretend to be what they really are not, when they <hi>draw near to God with their lips,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.13.</note> 
               <hi>but their hearts are far enough from him,</hi> when they think to put a cheat upon him, and their own Souls, and make Religion a cloak for all manner of impiety, this doth ſo far ſeparate betwixt God and them, that it cauſeth him to hide his face from them, till at laſt he appear very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable in his robes of vengeance, and then miſery, and confuſion is their inevitable lot and portion.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56367:16"/>
            <p> And if ſo, then in what miſerable circumſtances are we in again of this Nation, whoſe hypocritical actions do ſtill keep pace with ſuch deceitful Jewiſh Worſhippers? How ready are many of us to come and ſtand before God, to viſit his Courts, and to worſhip him in his Holy Temple? But we hope that it is no offence to bring our ſins along with us, that our Fraud and Oppreſſion, our Pride and our Covetouſneſs, our Lying and our Slandering, our Malice and Uncharitableneſs may bear us Company to the Church, and yet we our ſelves are no leſs acceptable to God Almighty, as if God was obliged to us for the outward formalities of his Worſhip, and might very well afford to let us have our ſins into the bargain, as if Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was better than Obedience, and the labour of the Lips was much to be preferred before the true homage of the Heart: And that this is too true, daily experience may convince us, for may we not ſee ſome to day in the Church, complementing God into a belief, that they are his Servants, when behold to morrow we ſhall find them either the Devils ſlaves, or the Worlds drudges? May not we obſerve ſome to day very devout towards God, whom to morrow we ſhall find ready to devour their neighbour? Bleſſing God to day, and curſing men to morrow? Praying to Chriſt now perhaps with ſome fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency, and anon with no leſs vigour belying and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, or oppreſſing their fellow-Chriſtian? Hearing a Sermon one hour, and the very next reſolving to act and do clear contrary to what they hear? And can we think that God will accept of ſuch worſhippers as theſe? That ſuch monſters made up of light and darkneſs, ſhall be as dear to him as his Children, or that ſuch a form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs will be as grateful as, the power of it? if we do we are ſtrangely miſtaken, for believe it, ſuch things as theſe are the higheſt provocations, and if we in this Nation perſevere and continue in them, if we take a delight in playing the Hypocrites, and make Religion a cloak
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56367:16"/>for the fouleſt abominations, it is but juſt for God to take from us that Religion which we ſo groſly abuſe, to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our fallacies, and diſcover our ſecret wickedneſs, and make us appear by the dreadfulneſs of his judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, to be what we really are, a deceitful, impious and incorrigible Generation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This, I ſay, God may and will do if we do not time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevent it, but, God be thanked, there is yet a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility that this may be done, God, I hope, hath not paſt an irrevocable Sentence upon us, but we may yet reverſe it, if we pleaſe, our ſelves; now by what means and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods this may certainly be accompliſhed is the third and laſt Head of Diſcourſe I am to ſpeak to.</p>
            <p>And here, though I might inſtance in divers things which would be very effectual to this purpoſe, yet I ſhall contract them all to three, and leave them then to your ſerious conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It will be very requiſite for you to ſet a due value and eſtimation upon that Church and Religion which is now eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To humble your ſelves before God, and be inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in your prayers and ſupplications to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To caſt away all thoſe ſins and abominations, which, by reaſon of their heinouſneſs, cry to Heaven for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and may juſtly provoke God to plague us with ſuch a judgment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Learn to ſet a true value and eſtimation upon that Church and Religion which is now eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, for that will be one means for God to preſerve and to continue it to us. He that duly weighs and conſiders with himſelf, not only the preſent way of worſhip which is eſtabliſhed in our Church, but the purity of its Doctrine, and the excellency of its Inſtitutions, as he will find, that it is not poſſible for him, in any other Church of the World, to be a more honeſt man, a more dutiful Subject, and a better Chriſtian, than he may be in the Fellowſhip
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56367:17"/>and Communion of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſo ought he upon ſuch conſiderations to have the greateſt eſteem, and honour and kindneſs for this Church, which doth the beſt deſerve it.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe this regard and eſteem cannot be better expreſſed than by laying aſide all unjuſt and undue preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt it, and by an unanimous embracing all its holy ſanctions, therefore muſt theſe two things be careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved by him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is very neceſſary, in order to the ſetling men in a due regard and eſteem for our preſent Church, to lay aſide all unjuſt prejudices againſt it: it was ever for the honour of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that her Principles and Doctrines were always found true from error and falſity, that in matters of faith ſhe ſtill kept up to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Rule, and never enjoyned any thing to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a truth, but what the word of God did ſufficiently confirm, and the firſt and pureſt Ages of Chriſtianity did aſſert and maintain to be ſo: and for what concerns all her outward Rites and Ceremonies, all her Government and Inſtitutions; although ſome of her unnatural and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient Sons have, upon this account, beſpattered her reputation, and flung durt in her face, and have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to pollute her Garments, and ſubvert both her Order and Diſcipline, and like the Children of <hi>Edom</hi> in the day of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. cxxxvii. <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</note> have cryed, <hi>Down with her, down with her even to the ground;</hi> yet theſe have been ſo fully evinced to be only the effects of the deepeſt malice and envy, that we find the judicious <hi>Hookers</hi> aſſertion, in his Preface to his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity</hi> ſtill abundantly verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: That ſurely the preſent form of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which the Laws of this Land have eſtabliſhed, is ſuch, as no Law of God, no Reaſon of man hath hitherto been alledged of force ſufficient to prove they do ill, who to the uttermoſt of their power withſtand the alteration thereof; and contrariwiſe, the other, which inſtead of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56367:17"/>it we are required to accept, is only by error and miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit called the Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, no one proof as yet brought forth, whereby it may clearly appear to be ſo in very deed, And if ſo, why ſhould any one be prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt that Church, which doth not command any thing contrary to the word of God, or which is not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the firſt and pureſt Ages of Chriſtianity? Why ſhould any one be ſo unreaſonable to ſeparate from a Church, which is <hi>ſtupor mundi,</hi> the amazement of the world for Piety, Learning, and true Religion, only by reaſon of a few outward modes and Ceremonies, when nevertheleſs thoſe very Ceremonies contain nothing in them, which is any way inconſiſtent with the ſubſtantial parts of Religion, but are very uſeful and neceſſary to beautifie and adorn it? I ſay, who would any longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert this Church upon ſuch grounds as theſe are, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when we conſider that ſuch prejudices as theſe give the greateſt advantage to our common Enemy, the Pope, whilſt by our difference about trifles, he takes an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to open the gap wider, to foment our Diviſions, and increaſe the Schiſm, and come upon us unawares whilſt we are at variance amongſt our ſelves, and ſo work the ruin and downfal of us all?</p>
            <p>And then tell me, whether would the yoke of the Church of <hi>England</hi> or of <hi>Rome</hi> be more intolerable? Which do you think would be more eaſie to you, the bloody Court of Inquiſition, or the Conſiſtory of our Biſhops? Which would be moſt grateful, a few innocent Ceremonies in our Church, or the conſtant practice of ſuperſtition in theirs? Which would be moſt acceptable, a grave Liturgy of Prayers directed to God alone, in a Language which you all underſtand, as it is in ours, or an extravagant Form of Prayers to Saints and Angels, and in a Tongue too of which you are ignorant, as it is with them? in fine, whether, had you better adhere to a Church which is guilty of the greateſt corruptions, both in faith
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56367:18"/>and manners, as it is at this day evident in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> than ſubmit to a Church which is free from all ſuch things as it is at this day with the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if theſe things ſtrike a dread and terror into you, if the Popiſh Tyranny doth affect you with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and you tremble to think of their cruelties and perſecutions towards thoſe who do not embrace their monſtrous Tenents and Doctrines, have a care you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke not God to deliver you up once more to their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and leave you to be inſlaved and tortured by the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> for your uncharitable practices towards the Church of <hi>England,</hi> let not your unjuſt cavils and aſperſions, your prejudices and ill will you bear towards it enforce him to take it away from you, ſince you know not how to value the bleſſing you enjoy by the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, and leave you to be blinded with the ſpirit of Error and Idolatry; but be at laſt perſwaded to open your eyes, and have but once a due regard to that Churh, whoſe Docttines are ſo ſound, whoſe Principles are ſo firm, and whoſe integrity ſo unqueſtioned.</p>
            <p>And when once you have ſo far conſidered its worth and excellency, as to eſteem and value it as you ought to do, by laying aſide all your prejudices againſt it, you will then quickly be perſwaded with one heart, and one mind, to embrace all thoſe ſanctions and inſtitutions which ſhe thinks fit to enjoyn you, which is the ſecond thing I ſhall propoſe to you.</p>
            <p>Unity is the very Bond, and Cement of all Chriſtian Society, and 'tis impoſſible to make a rupture in that body which is tied, and kept cloſe together by this holy Ligature, and this our adverſaries know very well, and therefore though they endeavour unity as much as in them lies amongſt themſelves, becauſe it renders them very ſtrong and formidable, yet they have ſo far experienced the old Maxim, <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> that it hath been their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56367:18"/>buſineſs to cauſe their buſineſs to cauſe the greateſt divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſeparation amongſt us, that ſo they may make a prey of us, and like the Kite in the Fable carry away the feeble combatants whilſt they are pecking at one another with bents and bulruſhes: and to this purpoſe it is, that they are creeping into all houſes, and transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, like <hi>Proteus,</hi> into all ſhapes, hence it is that they counterfeit any manner of Sect, and cant in all tones, and adapt themſelves to all humours, and become all things to all men, though in another ſenſe that S. <hi>Paul</hi> did, even to ſeduce all. And now though we know this to be their project, and deſign to ſubvert Church and State, and are ſenſible they can no way better do it than by widening the breach of ſeparation, yet are we ſo fooliſh to hearken ſtill to the bewitching charms of theſe Sirens, till they draw us at laſt into the ſea of deſtruction? Hath not the wiſeſt man that ever lived told us that <hi>a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke xi. 17.</note> And did not the ancient <hi>Britains</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience this truth in this Nation, when by their mutual feuds and animoſities they fell a Sacrifice to their foreign enemies, for, <hi>dum pugnant ſinguli vincuntur univerſi?</hi> Nay have we not great reaſon to believe what ſome conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons have affirmed upon very probable conjectures, that if ever Popery came in amongſt us, it would moſt certainly creep in through the back door of Separation? And yet for all we know, and are forewarned of this, ſhall we give the opportunity to theſe <hi>Philiſtins</hi> to bind us, and take from us our ſtrength by cutting away the locks of Unity that would make us invincible? Were you ever in more danger than at this time? Do you not ſee theſe mad Bulls of <hi>Baſhan</hi> ramping and roaring,
<note place="margin">Pſal. xxii. 12, 13.</note> and gnaſhing upon you with their teeth? Upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count there was never a more abſolute neceſſity to forget all animoſities, to lay aſide all unneceſſary cavils and ſcruples than now, and to join your forces together with one conſent,
<note place="margin">John xi. 48.</note> leſt <hi>the</hi> Romans <hi>ſhould come and take away
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56367:19"/>both your place and Nation.</hi> Join therefore your hands and hearts together, and become as one people, for ſuch a bleſſed Union would fruſtrate all the deſigns and plots of our enemies, it would become a brazen wall of defence round about us, which they would never be able to undermine, or caſt down, it will put them quite out of heart, and daſh all their hopes, it would take away from them all advantages, and put them to their laſt ſhifts; nay in fine, 'tis the only way to continue peace and happineſs to the Nation: for God who is the God of peace, of order and unity, would then begin to take a delight in us, and protect us under the ſhadow of his wings from all the outward violences and ſecret machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſons of Belial, and if we could once be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to arrive at ſo good, and holy a temper of mind, as <hi>with one heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. xv. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and one voice to glorifie God even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> this would ſo far endear him to us as to enſure him on our ſides, and to gain his Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage; and then let men or devils combine againſt us, and threaten our Church with ruine and deſolation, <hi>He that ſitteth in the Heavens would laugh them to ſcorn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. ii. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord would have them in deriſion:</hi> and as he would defeat all the evil contrivances of our enemies againſt it, ſo would he raiſe it to greater beauty and luſtre, and eſtabliſh it upon ſuch firm, durable and laſting foundations, that the gates of Hell ſhould never be able to prevail againſt it: Since then theſe would be the joyful effects of Unity, ſince this would make God to be our peculiar Guardian, and us to be his more eſpecial favourites, ſince this would be a means to ſecure us from all our enemies, and reduce us to a bliſsful, and a flouriſhing condition, if either you deſire to deſire to promote the common intereſt of your Religion, or your Brethrens welfare, or your Nations happineſs, let <hi>S. Pauls</hi> advice ſink down in your hearts, and appear practicable in your lives; <hi>I beſeech you, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. i. 10.</note> 
               <hi>by the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you all ſpeak
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56367:19"/>the ſame things, and that there be no diviſions amongſt you, but that you be perfectly joined together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, as united hearts, minds, and judgments would become one very inſtrumental means to divert Gods Judgments from us, ſo would our joint concurrence in humbling our ſelves by Prayer and Supplication be another excellent way to move God to commiſerate our condition, and preſerve us from deſtruction. When <hi>Jonah</hi> came with that ſevere meſſage to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> that in forty days God was reſolved to deſtroy it, both nature, and the preſent danger they were in ſuggeſted it to them to addreſs themſelves in all humility to the ſupreme Being, who had ſent his Prophet to denounce that Judgment againſt them, and both King and People, Man and Beaſt was covered with ſackcloth, and they lift up their voices with one accord, and cried mightily to God to deliver them from that evil, which he threatned againſt them, and we find that they met with ſucceſs ſuitable to the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and fervency of their prayers, for <hi>God repented him of the evil, which he ſaid he would do to that City,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jonah 111.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>and did it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O let us follow the ſame method at this day, let us humble our ſelves before Almighty God, and if there be ever a <hi>Jacob</hi> amongſt us, any who can wreſtle and prevail with God, let him forthwith ſet about ſo glorious a work, for never was there more need of ſuch preſſing interceſſions: Alaſs, when we ſee our enemies ready to devour us, when we find they are reſtleſs in their plots and conſpiracies againſt us, 'tis ſure high time for us to fall to our prayers, and be as reſtleſs in our ſupplications to God Almighty to diſappoint them: and indeed if we were but once really ſenſible of our danger, as it would melt the ſtrongeſt heart living, and make it bleed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the miſeries that would enſue from hence, ſo would it make us fly forthwith with the greateſt ſpeed to Gods
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56367:20"/>Sanctuary, and there implore the Auxiliaries of Heaven to ſuccour and relieve us: and ſince we know not how long we may enjoy the bleſſed opportunity of treading in Gods Courts, and calling upon his name, and deprecating his judgments, as bleſſed be God, we do yet for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; ſince we are not ſure how ſoon we may be baniſhed from his Temples, be abridged of his worſhip, be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his word, and made to wander to and fro from this place to that place, from this City to that City, to ſeek that word, which yet we ſhall not be able to find, why do not we make the beſt uſe of it whilſt me may? Why do not we aſſemble more unanimouſly together, and with whole Volleys of Prayers ſtorm the gates of Heaven, and enforce God to ſtand up for us, and to become our defence and refuge? If your Houſes were like to periſh in a general Conflagration, would you not all run to quench the fire with the greateſt celerity? And when the whole Kingdom is ready to be put into a flame by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of turbulant Popiſh Incendiaries, will not you be as ready to uſe all poſſible means to obſtruct and allay it? Now ſince nothing can be more effectual to this purpoſe than Prayer, why are we ſo back ward in the performance of this Holy Duty? What is the reaſon our petitioners are ſo few, and the Houſe of Prayer ſo empty and unfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented? Alas, Can we think that God will do what we would have him, though we ſay nothing at all to him, or that a ſhort, ſlight, ſleepy-hearted addreſs now and then, when we pleaſe, will ſerve the turn? Can we hope to bind Gods hands with withs and ſtraws, to arreſt his vengeance with weak and feeble Aſſaults? What our Saviour ſaid in another caſe, that this kind, ſpeaking of ſuch Devils as had got poſſeſſion of mens bodies,
<note place="margin">The Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> in his late Sermon before the Houſe of Lords.</note> goeth not out but by Prayer and Faſting; may be ſaid of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> the Devils of Sedition and Faction, of Treaſon and Rebellion, thoſe Familiars of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and St. <hi>Omers,</hi> as they are juſtly ſtiled by the greateſt Prelate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56367:20"/>in this Nation, which have ſo long poſſeſſed and agitated a wretched part of this Kingdom, they are not to be quelled eaſily or driven out from hence, but by the moſt ſerious humiliation, and by the moſt fervent prayers and ſupplications of holy Votaries: then let our hands never wax heavy, but be always held up like <hi>Moſes,</hi> in a devout importunity; let us conſider, and lay to heart what great need we have now more than ever, to be conſtant at Church, and devout at our prayers, and from thence be perſwaded with one accord to perform this ſo acceptable a duty, let us lift up our hearts and voice in ſome ſuch petition as that of Holy <hi>David, O,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſai. lxxiv. <hi>ver.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>deliver not the ſoul of thy turtle dove to the multitude of the wicked, forget not the congregation of the poor for ever. Ariſe, O God, plead thine own cauſe, remember how the fooliſh man blaſphemeth thee daily. Forget not the voice of thine enemies, the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult of thoſe that riſe up againſt thee increaſeth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Now if to ſuch ardent Petitions as theſe we add in the laſt place a true and ſerious Reformation of what is amiſs amongſt us, then will God be intreated for the Land, and become gracious unto us: but indeed without this there is very little hopes of it; for can we think that when continual provocations are offered to him, he will ſtill connive at them, and bear with them? Can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that when the blaſphemies of the profane, the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualities of the voluptuous, and the mockeries of the Hypocrite ſend up daily challenges to Heaven, this will not at laſt overcome Gods patience and long-ſuffering, awake him to vindicate the honour of his name, and not ſuffer it any longer to be thus proſtituted and polluted? Will the deepeſt ſighs, or the loudeſt clamours to Heaven be able to drown our impieties, or the moſt importunate Petitions make an atonement for our tranſgreſſions? no, the wiſe man hath told us,
<note place="margin">Prov. xv. 8.</note> 
               <hi>That the prayer of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord,</hi> and it was the blinds mans
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56367:21"/>Divinity in the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Joh. ix. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Now we know that God heareth not ſinners;</hi> and therefore it was well obſerved by St. <hi>Cyril,</hi> that it was very abſurd, for thoſe who come by Prayer to obtain mercy, to provoke the Divine Law-giver another way by not doing what he commands. The only way to have all our ſupplications anſwered by God with a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous return, is to make our lives the tranſcripts of our Prayers, not only to pray againſt ſin, but to endeavour to relinquiſh thoſe ſins we pray againſt, not only to beg of God that he would enable us to perform his Holy Laws, but actually to ſet our ſelves about the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that which we crave of him: and unleſs we do thus, our Prayers are but the labour of the Lungs, which, like bellows, make the fire of Gods anger burn fiercer, but do not blow it out: therefore, ſaith God to the <hi>Jews, When you ſpread forth your hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>I will hide my face from you;</hi> when you make many Prayers I will not hear, and what was the reaſon of this? the following words tell you, <hi>your hands are full of blood:</hi> As if God had ſaid, you come and worſhip in my Temple, and offer up the Sacrifice of Prayer to me, but you keep your old ſins, and ſtick cloſe to your former tranſgreſſions, and this makes me hate and abominate all your ſervice; but then, as he reproves them ſeverely for ſuch Hypocriſie, ſo in the next place he preſcribes them a way to regain his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.
<note place="margin">Verſe 16, 17, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Waſh you make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to evil, learn to do well, ſeek judgment, relieve the oppreſſed, judg the fatherleſs, plead for the widow;</hi> Come now, and let us reaſon together, though your ſins be as ſcarlet they ſhall be white as ſnow, though they be red as crimſon, they ſhall be as wooll. If ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of the Land, but if ye refuſe and rebel, ye ſhall be deſtroyed by the ſword: The ſame advice is given them by <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. xvii. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Truſt ye not in lying words, ſaying, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56367:21"/>theſe. For if ye throughly amend your ways and your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; if ye thoroughly execute judgment between a man and his neighbour; if ye oppreſs not the ſtranger, the fatherleſs and the widow, and ſhed not innocent blood in this place, neither walk after other Gods to your hurt; then will I cauſe you to dwell in this place in the Land that I gave to your fathers for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that you ſee upon what terms 'tis God ſuſpends his judgments, 'tis upon repentance and amendment, and therefore we find in the inſtance I gave you before of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neveh,</hi> that when they there did turn away every one from his evil way, and from the violence that was in their hands, God had mercy on them, and deſtroyed them not; by which we may find what we of this Nation are now to hope and truſt to; for the reſult of all in this, if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in our diſobedience and impenitency, in our contempt of God and Religion, in Profaneneſs and Hypocriſie, ſuch things will moſt certainly make us ripe for Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, but if we reclaim our evil ways, and reform what is amiſs; if we worſhip God more devoutly, and pray unto him ſincerely, and repent unfeignedly, then will God preſerve us ſtill from our enemies, all the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits and Emiſſaries of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall never be able to do us any prejudice, but our Church ſhall ſtill flouriſh, and our Kingdom ſhall enjoy greater meaſures of happineſs, and we ſhall all ſit under our Vines and our Figg-trees to eat the fruit of our labour in peace and tranquillity.</p>
            <p>I will conclude all therefore with the Prophet <hi>Zephani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah's</hi> advice, and let us all endeavour to treaſure it up care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in our hearts: <hi>Gather your ſelves together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph. ii. 1, 2, &amp; 3.</note> 
               <hi>before the decree bring forth, before the day paſs as the chaff, before the fierce anger of the Lord come upon you: Seek ye the Lord, all the meek of the earth, which have wrought his judgment, ſeek righteouſneſs, ſeek meekneſs: it may be you ſhall be hid in the day of the Lords anger.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:56367:22"/>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:56367:22"/>
            <head>GODS CALL TO Weeping and Mourning.</head>
            <head type="sub">SERMON II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH xxij. 12, 13, 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And in that day did the Lord God of Hoſts call to weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to mourning, and to baldneſs, and to girding with ſackcloth.</p>
                  <p>And behold, joy and gladneſs, ſlaying Oxen, and killing Sheep, eating Fleſh, and drinking Wine: let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall die.</p>
                  <p>And it was revealed in mine ears by the Lord of Hoſts, Surely this iniquity ſhall not be purged from you till ye die, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is not long ſince we kept a Day of Humiliation to implore Gods Mercy, and deprecate his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ſeemed to hang over our heads, by a bloody Plot contrived by Papiſts, to murder our King, to ſubvert our Religion, and enſlave our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by reducing it again under the <hi>Romiſh Yoke,</hi> a Yoke which neither we nor our Forefathers were able to bear.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56367:23"/>
            <p> And he that conſiders with himſelf how ready and active the Devil is, who was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>a murderer from the beginning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John viii. 44.</note> ſtill to inſtigate and ſpur forward his Agents, to ſet Kingdoms in flames, and make the Streets ſwim with the Blood of good and holy Chriſtians; how willingly the Jeſuits, who be his chiefeſt Factors, do obey ſuch diabolical motions, under what unhappy circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances we of this Nation are for the preſent by reaſon of our manifold and potent enemies abroad, our private feuds and diviſions at home, and above all our open da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and notorious ſins and abominations, which juſtly call aloud to heaven for vengeance upon us, will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be perſwaded that a ſecond day of Humiliation is no leſs neceſſary than the former, which it is much to be feared was not obſerved with thoſe hearty reſentments of indignation againſt our ſins, with thoſe ſincere teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of outward and inward contrition, and with thoſe cordial reſolutions of future reformation and amendment, which the grievouſneſs of the Judgment, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the danger impendent over us did juſtly require at all our hands.</p>
            <p>And now that the drowſy may be awakened, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant inſtructed, the negligent excited, the improvident forewarned, and all of us deeply affected with a true ſenſe of our condition, and by a timely repentance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent thoſe calamities which threaten the extirpation of the Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Polity amongſt us, I have made choice of theſe words of the Prophet, wherein God ſeems now to give us as ſeaſonable a call, as he did then to the <hi>Jews: And in that day did the Lord God of Hoſts call to weeping, and to mourning,</hi> &amp;c. From which words there are three things will fall under our conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The unſpeakable Mercy and Kindneſs of God to the <hi>Jews,</hi> in calling them to a ſolemn and ſerious humiliation; Ver. 12. <hi>In that day did the Lord God of Hoſts call to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56367:23"/>weeping, and to mourning, and to baldneſs, and to girding with ſackcloth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The horrible Ingratitude of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who inſtead of humbling themſelves before God, went on in their former habituated courſes of voluptuouſneſs, and ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality: For <hi>behold</hi> ver. 13. <hi>joy and gladneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The aſtoniſhing Reſolution of God upon their not hearkning to, and obeying that gracious call, <hi>viz.</hi> to root them out and deſtroy them: Ver. 14. <hi>Surely your iniquity ſhall not be purged from you till you die, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. I begin with the firſt of theſe, the unſpeakable mercy and kindneſs of God to the <hi>Jews,</hi> in calling them to a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and ſerious Humiliation: <hi>In that day did the Lord of Hoſts call to weeping, and to mourning,</hi> &amp;c. Whether this call was by his Prophet threatning them with ſome ſevere Judgment for their perſeverance in iniquity, or whether by ſome ſmart Judgment which God thought fit to lay upon them, he endeavoured to reclaim them from the evil of their ways, and bring them to a ſight and ſenſe of their follies before their final extirpation, 'tis certain that either or both of theſe calls were very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive of his loving kindneſs towards them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For firſt, it argues the great Care and concernment God had ſtill for their Nation, how ſollicitous he was to preſerve, and to continue it, to protect and to defend it, to make them ſtill a glorious and a flouriſhing people, happy in themſelves, and a terror to their enemies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſecondly, it was an argument of his Patience and forbearance, in ſparing and reprieving them from puniſhment when they moſt deſerved it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And thirdly, it was an incentive to their Duty, a <hi>memorandum</hi> to put them in mind, what courſe they ſhould take under ſuch gracious methods, namely to fall <hi>to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldneſs, and to girding with ſackcloth;</hi> that is, by ſuch outward lugubrious ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56367:24"/>of body, as well as an inward anguiſh and vexation of ſpirit, to declare their ſincere hatred of all ſin, and reſolution of amendment.</p>
            <p>So that from hence here will be three things to be inſiſted upon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Providence of God in taking care of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Communities of Mankind, he ſuffers not things to go at random in them, but he diſpoſeth of them as he thinks fit, and when there is a neceſſity he calls to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Patience and forbearance, he doth not puniſh without giving them notice, he calls them firſt, and then he ſtrikes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The End of all his gracious calls, 'tis to work in them a thorough humiliation for their tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, I ſhall conſider the Providence of God in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king care of Kingdoms, and Communities of Mankind, where all things do not happen by chance, but the divine diſpoſal of God Almighty, who calls to them, and exerts his power amongſt them when there is occaſion for it. It was a fond and ſtrange opinion of the <hi>Epicureans</hi> of old, that God was ſo taken up with the contemplation of his own excellencies and perfections, that he would not ſo much as vouchſafe to caſt one glance down upon theſe Sublunary Regions; that it was below the Majeſty of Heaven to be concerned in the pitiful affairs of poor earthly miſcreants, and to be angry at their follies, or ſeem to applaud their actions, was irreconcileable with the Divine Happineſs, which was unmixed and pure, free from any thing that might diſturb or diſquiet it: a fancy no doubt which <hi>Lucian</hi> gathered from their Schools, (in which he was no ſmall proficient, as a learned and worthy perſon tells us) for he brings in old <hi>Japetus</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> tipling Nectar together,
<note place="margin">Archdeacon of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in his Book <hi>De Deo &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntia.</hi>
               </note> and ſpending their time in telling old ſtories, <hi>Saturn</hi> confeſſing that he was gouty, which gave occaſion to the Poets to write, that he was fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56367:24"/>by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> to whom as being the younger, and more active, he reſigned the thunder, and the Kingdom, not troubling himſelf with hearing mens prayers, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their offences, that being a troubleſome and irkſome piece of ſervice. But if God Almighty be thus confined to Heaven, and his Providence doth not expand it ſelf over all the Univerſe, what account can be given of the eſtabliſhment of one Kingdom upon the ruines of another; that one Nation, whoſe Senators are wiſe and politick, whoſe Armies are ſtrong and numerous, whoſe People are warlike and couragious, ſhould fall a prey to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is far inferiour to them, either in wiſdom or conduct, in ſtrength or policy? How can this poſſibly be ſolved but by admitting that it is God who weakens and infatuates the one, and ſtrengthens, and gives aſſiſtance to the other, and by that means declares himſelf to be the Perſon alone that ſetteth up one Kingdom, and plucketh down another, as it ſhall ſeem good to him in his wiſdom and juſtice. Look we but abroad into the revolution of ſome of the grand Empires and Kingdoms of the world, and we ſhall find this truth abundantly verified. Tell me, what could make <hi>Cyrus</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> ſo puiſſant and victorious over the fierce Nations of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> but that God who raiſed him up, and called by his name long before he was born, was an aſſiſtant to him, and crowned him with ſucceſs by leading him into <hi>Babylon,</hi> when that City was moſt ſecure, full of wine and jollity, at an anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary feaſt, by a way they little dreamed of? And what could entitle the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Prince <hi>Alexander</hi> to ſo great Victories over the <hi>Perſians,</hi> but that God infatuated their Counſels, and gave him ſuch advantages, which if he made but uſe of, he could not fail of ſucceſs? It might ſeem ſtrange to ſome, that the cowardly <hi>Goths,</hi> and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>Vandals,</hi> and deſpicable <hi>Hunns,</hi> ſhold make ſuch devaſtations in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, which had been a terrour to the greateſt part of the World, and that in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56367:25"/>fifty years time more of it ſhould be loſt and deſtroyed, than had been conquered in a thouſand; but when again 'tis conſidered that the hand of God was in this deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that ſomething which was divine over-ruling all the Counſels and Stratagems of the graveſt <hi>Roman</hi> Senators, made that Nation at laſt improſperous in all their enterprizes, we may juſtly ceaſe our wondering, and conclude with <hi>Solomon,</hi> that <hi>the race is not always to the ſwift,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. ix. 11.</note> 
               <hi>nor battel to the ſtrong,</hi> but that God ordereth and diſpoſeth all things as ſeems moſt expedient to his infinite wiſdom.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer to the Text, how often did the <hi>Jews,</hi> with a handful of men, work miracles againſt their ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt enemies? How many Cities did they deſtroy? How many Fortreſſes did they demoliſh? What Armies did they put to flight, and how many Nations did they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due, and that many times by ſuch unlikely means, by ſuch weak forces, and under ſuch unhappy circumſtances, that nothing can be plainer, that if ſo be God had not preſided in their Councils, inſpirited them with courage, removed all difficulties, and fought their battels, it had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them to have effected ſuch wonderful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits: but now although he had taken ſo great care of them, had ſubdued all the Nations under them, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them the Land of the Heathen for an inheritance, yet to ſhew them likewiſe that he had ſtill the ſame power to diſpoſe of them and their Kingdom to other people, as he had done of other Kingdoms to them; he calls to them to learn ſo much duty from his care and his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence over them, as to humble themſelves under his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hand, leſt he ſhould make them as great a prey to their Enemies as their Enemies had been to them;
<note place="margin">Deut. ix. 4, 5.</note> for as it was not for the righteouſneſs or the uprightneſs of their hearts, that God gave poſſeſſion of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but for the wickedneſs of thoſe Nations did the Lord drive them out from before them, ſo would
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56367:25"/>he deal with them, and by the ſame Arm of providence deſtroy them before the face of the Heathen, if they did not forſake the evil of their ways, and become obedient unto the voice of the Lord their God.</p>
            <p>You ſee then how far the Providence of God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to intereſt, and concern it ſelf with Societies of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; as there is no Nation, which is out of its reach, ſo there is none but hath felt the effects of its influence, and if we will but take the pains to trace it in thoſe footſteps which are viſible in this our Kingdom, we ſhall find ſuch evident marks, and notices of it amongſt us, as will juſtly call us to a ſerious humiliation for the further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of ſuch mercies towards us: that for theſe many years now together we of <hi>England</hi> have enjoyed a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and a glorious peace in our Nation, whilſt all <hi>Europe</hi> beſide hath ſwom in ſtreams of blood; that we ſhould all be exempted from the miſery of War, whilſt our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours round about us have been continually ſpoiled and haraſſed by the rapine and cruelty of the inſolent Soldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that the black Clouds, and frightful Hurricanes, which the Jeſuits have conjured up, ſhould not fall down in ſhowers of blood and vengeance upon our heads; that all the bold Popiſh Confederates, who, like St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Aſſaſſinates, had bound themſelves under the moſt ſolemn vows and obligations, that they would murder our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, maſſacre his Subjects, ſubvert our Church, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine our State, ſhould as yet be diſappointed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated in their machinations; to what can we juſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe all this, but to the gracious Protection and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God Almighty? Indeed, did not he ſpread his ſhady wings over us, and protect us, we ſhould ſoon fall under theſe Popiſh Cormorants clutches, ſo ſecret are their Plots, ſo cunning their Contrivances, ſo politick their Agents, and ſo numerous and reſolute are they in all their enterprizes: and could their ſtratagems prevail, and their devices take effect, how joyful would they be at
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56367:26"/>ſuch an accompliſhment of their deſigns! What Jubilees would be kept, could they but gain this Kingdom, or could they but once ſeize upon the Vineyards of our <hi>Naboths,</hi> how willingly would they feaſt and glut themſelves with their blood into the bargain! but, God be thanked, that we are as yet out of their power, that we are ſtill under the arms of Gods gracious Providence, that God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call us to humiliation, that ſo he may continue his protection over us, that he is pleaſed to give us notice upon what terms we may expect his further patronage, upon what conditions he will be a Patriot to our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, a Guardian to our Church, a refuge to us all in our greateſt dangers and extremities: and this is the firſt thing obſervable from Gods Call, the great care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment he hath for communities of mankind, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to repentance, that ſo they may become fit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for his Patronage and Protection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond thing obſervable from Gods Call is his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Forbearance in calling to men before he ſtrike: though their provocations are high, their wickedneſs ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hainous, and their ſins ripe for vengeance, yet he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently defers puniſhment, and gives them timely notice to prevent it by repentance. In the Patriarchal Age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Flood, though wickedneſs was grown rampant, and the manners of men very corrupt and vitious, God did not preſently pour down the vials of his wrath, but upbraid them firſt for their crimes by <hi>Enoch,</hi> who was an eminent Prophet in thoſe days (a fragment of whoſe Propheſie is ſtill extant in St. <hi>Judes</hi> Epiſtle) and only threaten them with vengeance upon their perſeverance in impenitency. Afterwards when the world grew worſe and worſe, and wickedneſs appeared with a brazen forehead, and violence had covered the face of the earth, when the promiſcuous mixtures of the Children of <hi>Seth</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> had produced Giants and mighty men, men ſtrong to do evil, and who had as much will as power, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56367:26"/>as <hi>Joſephus</hi> calls them, a race of men inſolent and ungovernable, ſcornful and injurious, and who bearing up themſelves in the confidence of their own ſtrength de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed all juſtice and equity, and made every thing truc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle under their extravagant luſts and appetites, a character which <hi>Lucian</hi> gives the men of this Age, ſpeaking of the time of <hi>Deucalion</hi> (their <hi>Noah</hi>) and the flood, for ſaith he <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men exceedingly contumelious were guilty of the moſt enormous and unrighteous actions, violating all oaths and covenants, throwing off kindneſs and hoſpitality, and rejecting all ſupplications and addreſſes made to them: I ſay, when mankind was grown to ſo prodigious a height of impiety, and this infection had ſpread it ſelf over all parts, and was become ſo epidemical, that all fleſh had corrupted their ways, and ſcarce any but <hi>Noah</hi> left to keep up the face of a Church, and the profeſſion of Religion: things being come to this paſs quickly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum'd the Divine Juſtice, and made the world ripe for vengeance; the patience of God was now tired out, and he reſolved to make mankind feel the juſt effects of his incenſed ſeverity: but yet in the midſt of judgment he remembred mercy, for he tells them, although he would not ſuffer his patience to be eternally proſtituted to the wanton humours of unreaſonable and wicked men, and although his ſpirit would not always ſtrive with them, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſceptabit,</hi> as ſome Divines render it, diſpute,
<note place="margin">Gen. VI. 3.</note> and reaſon with them, yet that he would bear with them 120 years longer, in order to their Reformation; ſo loth is God to take an advantage of the ſins of men, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come unto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Well, thus it was in the <hi>Antideluvian</hi> Age; and when the world was repleniſhed with new inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, who tempted and provoked the moſt high God afreſh, by ſuch ſins and abominations as were of the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt dye, yet God did not preſently open the treaſuries
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56367:27"/>of vengeance, and ſpeak their ruine, and decree their deſtruction, but ſtill endeavoured to reclaim them by ſeaſonable precautions, and deferred his puniſhment, and waited patiently for their amendment: and to inſtance in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was a people as ſignal for their perverſeneſs and rebellion as for the manifold favours they received from the Almighty, under the Parable of the Vineyard, God is pleaſed to give a clear demonſtration of the tender care, and regard he had ſtill for them notwithſtanding their reiterated provocations againſt him, for he made this Vineyard upon a very fruitful Hill,
<note place="margin">Iſa. v.</note> 
               <hi>and he fenced it, and gathered out the ſtones thereof, and planted it with the choiceſt vines;</hi> nay, he digged it, and dunged it, pruned it, and watered it, uſed all the art of cultivation, that might cauſe it to be fruitful, hoping and looking ſtill for ſome productions proportionable to his care and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry concerning it; nay, and when it ſtill, year after year, diſappointed his expectations, and brought forth wild Grapes inſtead of Grapes, he was loth to withdraw his kindneſs from it, but continued to dreſs and to manure it, and ſuffered it,
<note place="margin">Luke xiii. 7, 8, 9.</note> like the Figg-tree in the Goſpel, (an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem ſtill of the ſame People) further to treſpaſs upon his patience, and would not deſtroy it till there was no hopes of its improvement.</p>
            <p>And to apply this to our ſelves: Hath not God plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as choice a Vineyard in this Nation, and evidenced his Providence and his loving kindneſs towards it by cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivating and preſerving it for many years together in as ample a manner, as he did that amongſt the <hi>Jews?</hi> Hath any Church of the world received greater notices of his favour, more peculiar marks of his affection, or more ſignal teſtimonies of his care on it, than the Church of <hi>England,</hi> of which we profeſs our ſelves to be members? Hath not the Divine Omnipotency interpoſed it ſelf many times miraculouſly for its deliverance, and have we not been as fire-brands pluck'd out of the fire, reſcued from the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56367:27"/>moſt apparent dangers, ſnatch'd from the very jaws of death, and the pit of deſtruction? How frequently have the crafty Foxes of <hi>Geneva</hi> endeavoured to undermine us, and the wild Boars of <hi>Rome</hi> to root us up, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour us; and yet notwithſtanding all their ſecret Cabals, their ſlie inſinuations, and politick projections, have been diſappointed of their hopes, and fruſtrated in their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations? As nothing could be more cruelly contrived, than the preſent Popiſh Plot, ſo nothing could be more ſecretly managed, for as if the Devil and the Jeſuits had laid their heads together, and joyned in a league to ruin and diſpatch us, nothing could ſeem more to favour their barbarous enterprize: they had ſtrengthened themſelves againſt us with Foreign intereſts abroad, they had drawn into the confederacy many of their friends at home, a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Maſſacre was reſolved upon, and moſt of us to be entombed in the ruins of our Kingdom, whilſt they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected triumphant Trophies upon the piles of our mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and mangled Carkaſſes: but behold, when they thought themſelves moſt ſure, when they were pleaſing themſelves with the thoughts of a proſperous ſucceſs in their deſigns, the Lord in mercy looked upon us by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering their wicked intentions, by defeating their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed projects, and bringing to light their miſchievous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices and machinations againſt us; and though in juſtice, by reaſon of our manifold offences againſt him, he might have ſuffered us to be taken by their wilyneſs, to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared by their devices, and fall a prey to theſe malitious and blood-thirſty Boutefeus, yet he hath reprieved us for ſome longer time from their tyranny and cruel deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and is reſolved to try what effects this his gracious and merciful providence will have upon us, hoping ſtill that this his patience and forbearance will lead us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Which brings me to the third Conſideration I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed from the Text, the end of all Gods callings to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56367:28"/>'tis to work in them a thorough and ſincere humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for their tranſgreſſions; <hi>In that day did the Lord God of Hoſt call to weeping and to mourning, and to baldneſs, and to girding with Sackcloth:</hi> now although theſe put together are but the exteriour ſuperficies of repentance, yet they are very good ſigns and ſymptoms of the reality of its performance, and neceſſary in order to its accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God Almighty: a weeping eye and a blubber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cheek, a mournful heart and an afflicted ſpirit, a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified body and a penitent ſoul, (which I confeſs muſt be indiſpenſably ſuperadded to all the reſt) muſt needs become Sacrifices acceptable to God, and will at any time, no doubt, be very available to avert all preſent danger, to prevent all future puniſhment, or at leaſt to ſecure ſuch ſafety and deliverance, as may be moſt neceſſary, and expedient in the diſmal times of calamity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such humiliation is very neceſſary to avert all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent danger: though the hand of vengeance be lifted up, this can hinder the ſtroke, though the ſword of juſtice be drawn, this can hold it back, though the decree be iſſued forth, this may prevent the execution; for ſo ſaith <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. xviii. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>At what inſtant I ſpeak concerning a nation and concerning a kingdom to pluck up, and to pull down, and to deſtroy it: If that nation againſt whom I have pronounced, turn from their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, then I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them.</hi> I cannot give you a better inſtance than in that of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> God ſends his Prophet to them to aſſure them, that they had but forty days ſpace allowed them either to repent in, or to be deſtroyed:
<note place="margin">Jonah iii. 3.</note> upon this they being immediately ſtruck with the guilt of their own ſins, and the terror of this judgment ſet a part a ſolemn day, without any further delays, for faſting and humiliation, for they put on Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth from the leaſt to the greateſt, and cauſed their very beaſts to faſt as well as themſelves, that ſo, as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> obſerves, the bleating of the Sheep, and lowing of the Cattel, with ſuch other doleful notes might move the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56367:28"/>hearts of men ſtill to further ſadneſs, which is a great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative to repentance: and how did they ſpeed upon this? What ſucceſs did their contrition and humiliation meet with, even with the greateſt their hearts could wiſh or deſire, for God altered his purpoſes forthwith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this people; the Text ſaith,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>He repented of the evil he ſaid he would do unto them, and did it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are all alarum'd at the news of great dangers which hang over our heads, and who is ſo obdurate and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate amongſt us, as not to be affected with the horror of them? I am apt to think that the yoke of <hi>Rome</hi> is as dreadful to us as ever that of <hi>Egypt</hi> was to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nor did they more tremble at the name of the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Task-maſters, than we do when we hear of the leagues and frauds, the treacheries and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the ſeditions and inſurrections, the butcheries and maſſacres of the Popiſh Emiſſaries: but will our fears prevent our dangers, or our jealouſies become a bar to our miſeries? Will a bare antipathy againſt them keep us out of their reach, or a few weak ſighs, or inſignificant groans, blow away thoſe ſtorms that threaten both Church and State with inevitable deſtruction? No, the only cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain way to be eaſed of our cares, and have our fears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, is to gain God on our ſides by a timely humiliation, and then we need not fear what the malice of man can do unto us: indeed we are too apt to rely upon a weak arm of fleſh, to confide in the ſtrength and the policy, in the counſel and advice, in the conſultation and reſolutions of thoſe who preſide over us; thus we feed our ſelves with fancies, that if our Senators be but quick and ſagacious in making a thorough diſcovery of theſe wicked incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries, if our Magiſtrates be but ſpeedy in the execution of the Laws againſt them, if theſe Traitors be but brought to condign puniſhment for the preſent, and ſevere Laws be enacted for the ſecurity of the King, and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the State for future Generations, all things yet
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56367:29"/>will go well, and we may hope ſtill for glorious days of peace and tranquillity: but then we do not conſider, that when thoſe are diſpatched we have Traitors ſtill amongſt us at our own homes, within our own breaſts, I mean our Sins, which, if not executed likewiſe with no leſs rigour and ſeverity, will open ſtill a door, and let in others from abroad no leſs dreadful and peſtilential than thoſe are, when we think our ſelves moſt ſecure and out of danger. It was a ſmart anſwer which an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commander gave a <hi>French</hi> Captain in <hi>Normandy,</hi> who asking him, when he thought their Forces, which were called back for <hi>England,</hi> by King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, would return into thoſe parts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, replyed, When their ſins called for them. Yea, 'tis they which are the inlets to all the evil in the world, 'tis they make a gap, open the avenues for our Enemies to come upon us armed, and never believe the Seminaries of <hi>Rome</hi> will deſert this Nation, till by unfeigned repentance we have obſtructed their paſſage, and God, by reaſon of that ſhall think fit not to ſuffer them any longer to torment, and perſecute us: <hi>Humble then you ſelves under the mighty hand of God,</hi> 'tis the beſt way to avert preſent danger.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis as expedient likewiſe to prevent all future pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; Repentance is not only an antidote againſt preſent evils, but a moſt certain defenſative againſt all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calamities: we are very ready to believe, that if this Plot could be but thoroughly fifted; if the bottom of it could be dived into, the chief Abettors of it diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Confederates laid open, the Aſſociates brought to light, the whole Popiſh Faction would be ſo bafled and diſappointed, and their motion for the future watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch vigilancy, and caution, that they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to do us any more prejudice: But put the caſe this were true, ſuppoſe we could obviate all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, countermine all their Plots, be privy to all their Cabals, and receive weekly Bills of Intelligence from all their Conſults in <hi>Spain, Italy, France</hi> or <hi>Flanders;</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56367:29"/>they ſhould ſtill be ſo infatuated in their Counſels, divided in their intereſts, and ſo weakened by their ill ſucceſs, as nothing could come to any maturity which they projected againſt us; yet can we be ſo fooliſh to imagin that God hath no other workmen to make him Darts and Arrows than Papiſts, or no other executioners of his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance but Jeſuits? Alas, if our offences require it, there are inſtruments enough befide to ſerve God in his purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, he can raiſe up wicked Agents within our own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to ruin and deſtroy us; he can, if he pleaſe, make a Synedrial Claſſis of <hi>Geneva</hi> become as fatal to us as a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave at <hi>Rome,</hi> and permit a trumpet of Sedition in order to our downfall to be blown as loud out of a Fanatick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, as a Jeſuits Cloyſter: he can crumble us into Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Diviſions amongſt our ſelves, and make every Schiſmatical Sect amongſt us become his rod and ſcourge to chaſtiſe our wickedneſs and folly: nay, he need not go ſo far for executioners to diſpatch us, for he can raiſe up within our own bowels Miniſters of his wrath, as he ſerved <hi>Antiochus</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> to put a period to our lives and ſins together: and nothing but a ſerious and ſincere Repentance, though perhaps we do eſcape now, can give us any aſſurance that we ſhall not fall, for the future, by one or other of thoſe direful Aſſaſſinates.</p>
            <p>'Tis obſervable in all the States and Kingdoms of the world, as in <hi>Aegypt, Babylon, Jewry,</hi> &amp;c. whom God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to drink the dreadful cup of his fury, that their final impenitency was the cauſe of their deſtruction, and they might perhaps yet have flouriſhed and been in vogue in the world, had not their ſins intercepted the Divine Favour, and haſtened their ruin. There is nothing can make a Nation firm and durable, laſting and permanent, ſettle it upon ſuch foundations, as that when the rain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends, and the floods come, and the winds blow, they ſhall not be able to ſhake it, but Repentance alone, which will ſo fortifie and ſtrengthen it, that the gates of Hell
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56367:30"/>ſhall not be able to prevail againſt it: upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, if we would for ever promote the univerſal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of out Nation, prevent all future attempts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of its Enemies againſt it, and eſtabliſh it upon ſuch ſolid and laſting foundations, as no ſhocks of the moſt puiſſant aſſailants ſhall be able to demoliſh it, let us anſwer Gods Call, and fall to weeping and mourning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By which means, I dare aſſure you, that if we could not avert preſent danger, nor prevent future puniſhment, yet we may thirdly, without all peradventure, deliver our own ſouls; yea, this is the comfort that the truly penitent man receives, though Gods judgment fly abroad to the terror of the wicked,
<note place="margin">Pſal. lvii. 1.</note> though the ſtorms and bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of affliction do ariſe, yet either under the ſhadow of his wings will hide him,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. x. 13.</note> until thoſe calamities be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt, or elſe with the temptation make a way to eſcape, that he may be able to bear it: if the old Dragon caſt out a flame of fire to deſtroy the Church, if the Clouds of perſecution fall in ſhowers upon the penitent mans head, yet behold,
<note place="margin">Iſa. xliii. 2.</note> 
               <hi>When he paſſeth through the water, God will be with him, and through the rivers, they ſhall not overflow him, when he walks through the fire, he ſhall not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon him:</hi> nay, God hath decreed to ſet a mark upon his head, that ſo he may eſcape the fury of the deſtroyer; <hi>Set a mark upon the foreheads of the men that ſigh, and that cry for all the abominations, that are done in the midſt of her;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. ix. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>and to the others he ſaid, Go ye after him through the city, and ſmite, let not your eye ſpare, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have pity, ſlay utterly both old and young, both maids and little children, and women, but come not near any man upon whom is the mark.</hi> You ſee then upon terms, you may hope for ſafety in the gloomy days of Calamity; if your returns be proportionable to Gods gracious calls, if you exerciſe all the acts of true penance and contrition, though your Nation ſhould be conſumed in the day of the Lords anger, yet your repentance ſhall render you ſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56367:30"/>grateful a Sacrifice to him, as will cauſe him, not only to accept your perſons, but to ſecure and protect them, to be your ſhield and buckler, your high tower and defence in the greateſt extremities.</p>
            <p>And now this being the deſign of Gods gracious call to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> one would be apt to think that ſuch endearing methods of kindneſs ſhould have met with ſome ſuitable returns of duty, that ſuch cords of love ſhould have drawn the <hi>Jews</hi> to a compliance with Gods deſires, and ſuch <hi>Philtrum</hi>'s of mercy charm'd them into good nature, and a complaiſant obedience; nay, one would believe it almoſt impoſſible for intelligent beings, who had but any ſpark left of the ſenſitive part of humanity, not to be armed againſt future danger upon ſuch fair premoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and be perſwaded from thence to provide for their own ſafety, and conſult their own ſecurity, much leſs to be guilty of ſuch oſcitancy and ſupineneſs, ſuch obdura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and perverſeneſs, as neither to be won by love nor awed by fear, but to ſet up themſelves in oppoſition to God, their own ways in contradiſtinction to his, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, that becauſe God will have one thing, they will be ſure to act clear contrary to the Divine Pleaſure: and yet this was the caſe of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Text, which brings me to the ſecond obſervable.</p>
            <p n="2">II. To conſider their horrible Ingratitude towards God, who as it were, in defiance to his Almighty hand, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to joy and gladneſs, when God thought it moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to call to weeping and mourning; to ſlaying ſheep, and killing oxen, when God thought faſting and abſtinence to be moſt proper for them; nay, to eating and drinking, even downright luxury and profaneneſs, when God expected, by a mortified body and a penitent ſoul, to have received the earneſt from them of a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Reformation.</p>
            <p>From which unworthy procedure of this people to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, there will three things again fall under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:56367:31"/> 1. The baſe Nature and diſingenuous Temper of the <hi>Jews,</hi> thus boldly to thwart God in all his gracious deſigns towards them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their carnal Security which made them deaf to the loudeſt Calls, and regardleſs of all ſuch things which were of the greateſt moment and concernment to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their prodigious Luxury and Voluptuouſneſs, which laid their conſciences aſleep, and made them incredulous, hard-hearted and remorſeleſs, unfit to relent at any thing, which was threatned againſt them, or to receive any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine favour or kindneſs that was offered them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall conſider the diſingenuous Temper, and baſe Nature of the <hi>Jews,</hi> thus to thwart God Almighty in the moſt gracious deſigns, and purpoſes concerning them. 'Tis the opinion of ſome Divines, that one reaſon why God was pleaſed to make choice of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people, and ſelect them from all the reſt of the world beſide, was indeed out of meer pity and compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, becauſe he knew they were a ſort of men of the moſt obſtinate, refractory and unmanageable tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per beyond all other Nations throughout the Univerſe, and therefore ſtood moſt in need of it: and indeed had they not been of ſo untractable a diſpoſition, and of a mold quite differing from all the race of mankind beſide, 'tis hardly ſuppoſeable, that under ſuch happy circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as God was pleaſed to place them, they could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have miſcarried, and become at laſt the off-ſcouring and the contempt of the world, had not their own unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd ingratitude opened a way for their ruin, and their incorrigibelneſs under all means expoſed them to ſuch misfortunes; and really, though they appeared in the ſhapes of men, yet that they ſeem'd to be deveſted of the common ſentiments and principles of humanity, will be too apparent to any one, who conſiders, that the moſt ſignal marks of the Divine Care and Providence left no more footſteps, nor made any more impreſſions upon
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56367:31"/>their minds and conſciences, than if they had been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but meer ſtocks and ſtones, Statues of Braſs, or Pillars of Marble. Who would not be perſwaded, that in the age of miracles, when God had delivered <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the hand of the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> by a mighty hand, and an out-ſtretched arm, by cauſing the <hi>Red Sea</hi> to be a Fortreſs to them, and a Grave to their enemies; this being an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting monument of Gods peculiar reſpect and regard to them, would not be likewiſe as laſting a <hi>memento</hi> of duty and obedience to them and their Poſterity to all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Generations? And yet no ſooner is the Song of praiſe for that deliverance out of their mouths, but they fall a murmuring and repining at the Author of it, as if he who had divided the Sea for their ſakes, could not as well open the treaſuries of Heaven, or ſoften the iron ribs of rocks to ſupply their exigencies; and when this was done too by miracle, and God had ſmote the rocks, that the waters guſhed out, and the ſtreams overflowed, <hi>When he commanded the clouds from above,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. lxxv.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 23, 24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>and opened the door of Heaven, and had rained down manna upon them to eat, and had given them of the corn of Heaven;</hi> yet for all this they ſinned ſtill, and the next news we hear of them, is,
<note place="margin">Pſal. cvi. 19.</note> that they choſe to worſhip a molten Calf before this God who had done ſo great things for them; by this means involving themſelves in the grievous guilt of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and provoking God to anger by ſuch extravagant inventions: I might give other inſtances to make good the Pſalmiſts character of them,
<note place="margin">Pſal. lxxviii. 8.</note> 
               <hi>that they were a ſtubborn and rebellious generation that ſet not their heart aright, and whoſe ſpirit was not ſtedfaſt with God,</hi> but the Text doth it ſo fully, that I need not go further; for that when God appears in his bloody robes of vengeance, and ſhakes the ſword of Juſtice over them, they nevertheleſs ſhould take ſo little notice of it as not to abate one inch of their jollity, but continue as merry and frolickſom, as if all was well, is an argument of the moſt perverſe incorrigible hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in the world.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:56367:32"/>
            <p> And I wiſh we be not found guilty of as baſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy requitals: we are all mightily ſurprized at the rumour and noiſe of a bloody Plot againſt us, and this heightens our fears, and increaſeth our jealouſies: but is our deportment ſuitable to ſuch dreadful apprehenſions, or do we behave our ſelves as men, whoſe preſent fear of danger is the genuine iſſue of the heart, and not barely of the tongue? doth the dreadfulneſs of ſuch a judgment cauſe any alterations in our perſons, becloud our counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances with ſorrow, bedew our cheeks with tears, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our hearts with ſuch paſſionate regrets, as the ruin of our State, the ſubverſion of our Church, and the horror of death or ſlavery may juſtly call for at all our hands?</p>
            <p>Alas, is not a quite contrary behaviour more diſcerni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amongſt us, and doth not our uninterrupted jollity, our unſeaſonable mirth, our exceſſive joy and gladneſs under all theſe circumſtances ſpeak our fears to be but counterfeit, or our jealouſies ſuperficial, and that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we may profeſs, we are not really concern'd for the good and intereſt of our Countrey? Is it an argument of any real care or ſincere affection in that Son, who when his Parents ſhall lie ſick, and are upon the very confines of Death and the Grave, ſhall follow his ſports, and indulge himſelf in pleaſure, ſhall frolick and carouze it, and be as brisk and bonny as if they were well and out of all fear of danger? And when the King, who is <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> the Father of our Countrey, when the Church, who is our Mother, when our Laws and Liberties ſeem all to lye at the ſtake, and are in the moſt apparent and imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger imaginable, can it be fitting or decorous for us to be guilty of ſuch things? Believe it, that is one way to force God to laugh and mock too, and then our laughter may chance to end in the moſt diſmal of all ſorrows, even in weeping to all eternity, and in wailing and in gnaſhing of teeth. Let us take heed then that this be not the reſult of our mad-brain'd jollity, but let us endeavour to prevent
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56367:32"/>it by mourning both for our own and the ſins of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; if we cannot redreſs them, yet let us heartily bewail the miſchiefs which we fear, and if the Church muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, at leaſt give her Funeral Rites, and if we cannot quench her flames, bedew her aſhes with our tears: thus we ſhall to good purpoſes invert the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> prepoſterous method, for which they are juſtly ſtigmatized, who, when God called to weeping and mourning, called aloud to joy and gladneſs, which argued the Baſeneſs and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs of their nature: and that is the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing obſervable from hence, in the <hi>Jews,</hi> is their carnal Security, who were utterly uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at all Gods Calls, and regardleſs of all ſuch things as were of greateſt conſequence and importance, and thinking themſelves out of danger, when deſtruction was at the door, call to joy and gladneſs, ſlaying oxen, and killing ſheep, &amp;c. It hath been a ſad fate which hath attended many people, to be infatuated with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt hopes of ſafety, and promiſe themſelves the greateſt meaſures of tranquillity, when deſtruction hath been coming upon them like an armed man: it ſeems the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſtill ſo great confidence in Gods favour, that they thought the moſt daring provocations could not poſſibly intercept it, and therefore ſtill cryed Peace, Peace, when the dangers were moſt apparent, and their ruin juſt at hand: but many Ages before them the ſpirit of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity had ſo ſeized the hearts of men, that nothing could remove thoſe <hi>Torpor</hi>'s which had benum'd them, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the fearful menaces, and thunderclaps that were ſent to awaken their lethargical conſciences, yet they went on in their old habituated courſes of ſin, being no more concerned at Gods voice, though it breathed out ſuch ſevere threatnings, than if it had approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with all the calmneſs imaginable, <hi>for they eat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke xvii. 27.</note> 
               <hi>they drank, they married wives, and were given in marriage.</hi> Let <hi>Noah,</hi> the Preacher of righteouſneſs, ſay what he would
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56367:33"/>to the contrary, until the very day that <hi>Noah</hi> entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ark, <hi>and the flood came and waſhed away all their filthy pollutions:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 28.</note> And ſo again in the days of <hi>Lot,</hi> they did eat, they drank, they bought, they ſold, they planted, they built, and when righteous <hi>Lot</hi> went to ſome of his friends to forewarn them of the evil which was coming upon them,
<note place="margin">Gen. xix. 14.</note> his words ſeem'd unto them like ſome idle ſtory or feigned Romance, and they would give no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the meſſage he delivered, till they felt the flames about their ears, and themſelves periſhing in the ruins of their City.</p>
            <p>And ſhould we calculate the number of ſuch like per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt us, I am afraid we ſhould find ſo large a roll of them, as might juſtly induce us to believe that their great Security is too fatal a Prognoſtick of our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Deſtruction: for ſome there are, who, unleſs they ſaw with their eyes the Popes Standard ſet up in <hi>England,</hi> and the Jeſuits waſhing their hands in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king blood of thoſe who are its Natives, will not believe that thoſe Religious Perſons by any means can be ſuch ſanguinary and cruel Butchers, notwithſtanding the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Hereticks (and we know whom they are pleaſed to aſperſe with that title) is a Doctrine taught in their Schools, juſtified by their practices, and maintained in their writings, as might be made appear from <hi>Ribadenei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, Becanus, Windeck, Stapleton,</hi> and the reſt of that lawleſs herd of <hi>Ignatian Caſuiſts:</hi> nay, is a Doctrine whoſe bloodineſs they can neither be able to conceal, nor waſh off from their Church, whilſt the Triumphant Oration of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth continues extant in the world, which he made to his Cardinals in the Conſiſtory at <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the barbarous Aſſaſſination of <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France,</hi> after he was ſtabbed to death by <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican Fryar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But others there are, who though they are perſuaded, that if indeed the power of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> was as extenſive
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56367:33"/>as their malice, and their intereſt as ſtrong as they could wiſh it were in <hi>England,</hi> both King and People might then ſuffer indeed, as the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> and in <hi>Ireland</hi> have done before them; but it being next to an impoſſibility for them ever to effect what we imagine they deſign, their caballs being now ſo narrowly watched, their ſecrecies diſcloſed, their intereſts weakned, and their own parties many times countermining their projects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the grand and moſt certain oppoſition they would be apt to meet withall from the greateſt part of this Nation, who 'tis to be hoped will never more be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to their monſtrous Doctrines and Tenents. Theſe things being conſidered, and they upon theſe grounds having ſuch unlikely hopes of ſucceſs, why men ſhould afflict themſelves with the terror of them, or dread their power, or be uneaſie, and concerned at their wild and extravagant attempts, argues too great levity and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence in them that do it, and therefore they reſolve, as for their own parts, let the Pope do his worſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult ſtill their own eaſe, and gratifie their own humours, and follow their own ways,
<note place="margin">Judg. xviii. 7.</note> and like the men of <hi>Laiſh</hi> live careleſs, and remiſs under all the revolutions, that may happen in the Kingdom. To ſuch men I anſwer, that ſuch Security is the readieſt inlet to the myſtery of Jeſuitiſm, for ſuppoſing that every body was as ſupine and careleſs as they, who would be left to ſearch into the intrigues, to obviate the deſigns, or to countermine the plots of theſe politick adverſaries? And then indeed would they triumph over our careleſneſs and ſecurity, and we ſhould as eaſily fall into their hands as they could deſire, and nothing could prevent this, but omnipotency it ſelf; but why God ſhould take care of them, who are ſo unwilling to take care of themſelves, why God ſhould not ſuffer them to make uſe of ſuch advantages as we afford them, but interpoſe his providence betwixt our Security and Ruine, is no way to be anſwered, unleſs we
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56367:34"/>will admit God to be the Patron of the ſlothful, or a Protector of thoſe who yet by their ſupinity fling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of the covert of his moſt ſacred Wings: ſo that if upon ſuch terms as theſe are men will promiſe themſelves ſafety, they are farther from it than they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or imagine; for if a man will ſtill compoſe himſelf to ſleep, when the floods are ruſhing in upon him, he muſt needs periſh by his fooliſh ſecurity, and if, when dangers are impendent, men will feed themſelves with hopes of eſcaping, and avoiding them, and yet uſe no means in order to prevent them, and though God calls to them, will not ſtep one inch out of the way, not part with one ſin, not relinquiſh one luſt, not abandon the leaſt pleaſure, though they are ſure to gain thereby Gods favour and protection, no wonder he at laſt ſuffers them to fall by their folly, and to periſh in thoſe calamities of which they thought themſelves moſt ſecure; this was the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> crime, for which God did juſtly upbraid, and puniſh them, and is a ſecond aggravation of their Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude towards him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing to be taken notice of, was the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable height of Voluptuouſneſs and Luxury to which they were arrived: the moſt powerful calls, the moſt amazing judgments, the moſt awakening menaces could not reclaim them from ſuch abominations, but being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to take their fill of pleaſure before God cut them off, in defiance of him they give their wills the full ſwing, indulge themſelves in all manner of ſenſuality, crying out in the <hi>Epicurean</hi> dialect, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row we ſhall die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he that conſiders how far the doctrine of <hi>Epicurus</hi> hath prevailed in this Age, how Gods Judgments, which have been very dreadful and aſtoniſhing amongſt us, have wrought clear contrary effects, to what they were deſigned, and having waſted the Seeds of natural Piety in us, have erected Academies of downright Atheiſm,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56367:34"/>and Voluptuouſneſs in the room, may juſtly conclude, that as we have out-vyed all the Jewiſh race of ſinners, ſo ought we likewiſe at laſt to tranſcend them in our pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. Look we but upon the practices and manners of this Nation, and we ſhall find this truth too ſadly exemplified, that the generality of men look upon themſelves, no otherwiſe than as creatures ſent into the world, as the Leviathan into the deep, to take his full career of paſtime and pleaſure in it; that they make it their buſineſs firſt to excite and cloy the fleſh, to ſpur it on to riots even beyond its own propenſions, by which means the year becomes but one mad Carnival, and all the Elements are muſtered up, and yet <hi>(nec Aer, nec Aqua, nec Terra ſufficit)</hi> all are not enough to careſs and ſatisfie their craving appetites:
<q>
                  <l>Aude aliquid brevibus Gyaris &amp; carcere dignum,</l>
                  <l>Si vis eſſe aliquid—</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To be aggrandized for wickedneſs was not only the great ambition of many <hi>Romans</hi> in <hi>Juvenal</hi>'s days, but is the deſire and chief aim of too many amongſt us, and he is reputed a man of excellent parts, a perſon of a very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined and delectable converſation, who dares venture to pull down the pale, or lay open the incloſures of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by the helliſh art of ſcoffing, or prophane jeſting at it: nay are there not ſome who are ſo bold as to ungod the world, and out-hector the devil, and reduce both to nothing, but imaginary phantaſms? Who endeavour to make Hell no more than ſome painted fire, and a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtate paſs for an impoſture of the Prieſt, and level all diſcourſes concerning it with the poetical deſcription of the <hi>Fairy-Land!</hi> And in theſe circumſtances no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the evil communications of ſuch men corrupt all good manners, no wonder that the empire of debauchery is ſo large, and that iniquity goes down with ſo great
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56367:35"/>ſatisfaction and delight, no wonder, that when men are willing to imbibe ſuch principles, their hearts and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads grow as hard as braſs,
<note place="margin">Jerem. vi. 15.</note> bluſh not, nor are aſhamed of the moſt filthy abominations, but publiſh their ſin like <hi>Sodom,</hi> and glory in ſuch things as have the greateſt tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitude and deformity: but if this deſperate condition was the moſt certain Symptom of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> deſolation: if the poor <hi>Britains</hi> of this Nation were then invaded by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> when they were grown to ſuch a height of luxury and prophaneneſs, that as <hi>Gildas</hi> ſaith, they were not only ſtrangers to Religion themſelves, but hated thoſe very perſons who had any ſenſe of it amongſt them; then may we juſtly dread the ſame fate will attend us, that our Atheiſm and Licentiouſneſs, our Pride and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs, will open a door, either for the Papiſts, or ſome other executioners of Gods vengeance to come in upon us, and deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>And this we may be convinced of to our eternal ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and confuſion, if we conſider Gods manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt all obſtinate and incorrigible ſinners, which brings me to the third Obſervable.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The aſtoniſhing Reſolution of God toward the <hi>Jews</hi> upon their not hearkening to, nor obſerving his gracious Call, namely, to devote them to the moſt bitter Plague of Death it ſelf: <hi>And it was revealed in mine ears by the Lord of Hoſts, ſurely this iniquity ſhall not be purged from you till ye die, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which we may learn that the mercies of God, when once they are abuſed, are always converted into the moſt direful plagues and puniſhments: God is ſaid in Scripture to have two rods, a rod of men, and a rod of iron, if the one cannot work upon our ſtony hearts, he will break them with the other; if men will not be bettered with the bread of affliction, he will feed them with wormwood: though,
<note place="margin">Exod. xxxiv. 6, 7.</note> 'tis true, God hath proclaimed himſelf merciful and long-ſuffering, yet he adds too, that he will by no
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56367:35"/>means clear the guilty; though he be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate lover of all mankind, and endeavours to draw them to him with the cords of love, yet if this will not do, he will chaſtiſe them with Scorpions: he puniſheth firſt gently, to try if that will work a reformation amongſt ſinners, but if ſuch mild puniſhments avail nothing, he then pours down upon them the utmoſt dregs of his fury: when they once come to ſuch a pitch of inſolency, as even with the Gigantick race of Rebels of old, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to fight againſt Gods Sacred Majeſty, he then makes their arrows recoil back upon their own heads: 'Tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable,
<note place="margin">Gen. xiv. 10.</note> that before the fatal judgment fell upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> God ſent ſome ſmaller puniſhments by the Invaſion of the Eaſtern Kings, who came againſt them, and diſcomfited them; and thus he dealt with the <hi>Jews</hi> before their final Captivity, he afforded them ſmaller in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his diſpleaſure, to tell us, that if little notices prove inſignificant amongſt us, greater marks of his fury ſhall leave deeper impreſſions on us; hence God is ſaid to have treaſuries of judgments, that will never be exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted whilſt men prove ſo expenſive in their ſins.</p>
            <p>Now that this way of proceeding is very juſt and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table towards all incorrigible ſinners will appear very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent upon theſe accounts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe there is no other way to deal with ſuch men but to make them the moſt formidable examples of his Juſtice; when men arrive at ſo great a degeneracy, they are paſt all ſenſe, and there is no hopes of recovery, they are altogether dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, and their conſciences are ſo obdurate; ſo frozen and ſo benumm'd that there is nothing can awaken, ſoften or mollifie them, no other means left to ſatisfie the offended juſtice of God but utter exciſion and deſolation: nay, there is no other way to deter others from ſuch habituated courſes of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as will in time induce ſuch fearful Lethargies upon the ſoul, than by inflicting the moſt heavy hand, and the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56367:36"/>ſevereſt rod upon the back of ſuch offenders, nothing will ſooner bring men to a ſenſe of their follies, and the practice of true Religion and ſubſtantial godlineſs, than ſuch terrible marks of the Divine vengeance, for when Gods judgments are ſo viſible in the earth the inhabitants thereof <hi>will learn righteouſneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah xxvi. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, there is no other way to give any tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſatisfaction to the abuſed mercy of God, but by ſuch ſevere proceedings: the greater the mercy, the greater is Gods reſentment of it, when abuſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the greater muſt be the puniſhment, and the more ſmart the retribution for the abuſe of it: if God do multiply his bleſſings upon men, and they debauch them to the worſt ends, what compenſation can he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive for the violation of ſuch kindneſs, but by making them the utmoſt objects of his fury, who ſpurned at all the bowels and the tenders of mercy? If a City ſhould fall into open rebellion againſt its King, and after all the gracious overtures of Peace and Reconciliation, ſtill hold out againſt him, and deny him admiſſion till his Sword forced the way through; would not this ſo far incenſe his abuſed patience and goodneſs, and make him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon its utter deſolation? And when we ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our provocations againſt God, notwithſtanding all the gracious terms and conditions he hath propoſed to us, will not his loving-kindneſs, which is tired out, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it ſelf into the hotteſt flames of indignation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the injury? Remember again the Parable of the Vineyard when God ſaw that after all his care, and his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over it, it was not bettered by his pruning, and brought forth nothing but wild Grapes, behold what ſevere things he threatens againſt it;
<note place="margin">Iſaiah v. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>I will take away the hedge thereof, and it ſhall be eaten up; and break down the wall thereof, and it ſhall be trodden down; and I will lay it waſte, it ſhall not be pruned, nor digged, but there ſhall come up Briars and Thorns: I will alſo command the clouds, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56367:36"/>they rain no rain upon it.</hi> Believe it, there is no ſury ſo extreme, as that which is bottomed upon repelled and irritated love; and God is then always moved to the higheſt wrath, when men take courage to ſin, becauſe grace doth abound.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But laſtly, ſuch wilful wickedneſs always enhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the guilt, and haſteneth the puniſhment. Thus when the Jews had beyond meaſure incenſed God Almighty by continual provocations, the judgments which fell upon them were proportionate to their offences, and it would make ones heart ake to read the Hiſtory of their Times, when in the ſpace of leſs than ſeven years there periſhed of the Jews, at home and abroad, both in their Civil and Foreign Wars (as <hi>Lipſius</hi> hath computed the number) no leſs than <hi>duodecies centena &amp; quadraginta millia,</hi> twelve hundred and forty thouſand men,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Conſtantia lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> to fulfil the tenor of thoſe threatnings which had ſo frequently been iſſued out by their Prophets againſt that Nation.</p>
            <p>And now ſince the mercies have been as great which God hath vouchſafed to us, and our incorrigibleneſs as remarkable under the greateſt of them, what remains for us, but a fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to devour all Gods adverſaries? What can we ſay for our ſelves, that God ſhould not ſuffer us to fall into their hands whom we moſt fear; ſince we have trampled upon his goodneſs, whom we have moſt reaſon to love? It is but juſt with God to puniſh one ſin by another, and ſo fit us for deſtruction by the permiſſion of it, to change our indifferency in Religion into a blind Zeal, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious practice of it; our open Prophaneneſs into pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Idolatry; our contempt of Order and Diſcipline into rigorous Cenſures and a bloody Inquiſition; our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing of Dominion and ſpeaking evil of Dignities, into a Yoke of Tyranny and Romiſh Uſurpations. And I know not what can any way avert the one, but our hearty and ſincere reſolutions to retract and utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56367:37"/>the other, and with proſtrate bodies and contrite ſouls unanimouſly to implore the divine mercy in that excellent Form of Prayer which our Church affords us for this occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>GLORIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S and gratious God, whoſe judgments againſt obſtinate offenders are moſt ſevere and terrible, but thy mercies inſinite to all, that with hearty repentance and true faith turn unto thee: We ſinful people of this Land do acknowledge before thee, to thy glory, and our own ſhame, that never any Nation had more experience of thy goodneſs, nor yet did ever any more unthankfully abuſe it: when thou gaveſt us great and long proſperity, we fed our ſelves to the full, waxed fat, and kicked againſt thee: when thou threweſt us into horrid confuſions, from which we ſaw then little hopes of ariſing, even in the time of that diſtreſs did we treſpaſs yet more againſt thee: when by miracles of mercy thou hadſt tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our captivities, we ſoon returned to folly, to our vomit, and to our wallowing in our former, or greater filthineſs. Even while thou haſt of late appeared for us, by diſcovering the Plots and Contrivances of our implacable enemies of the Romiſh Faction, we have been in the mean time by our ſins ſighting againſt Heaven, and againſt thee. And now we are no more worthy to be called either thy ſons or thy ſervants, whom neither thy fear hath driven, nor thy goodneſs led to repentance. In mercy awaken our drowſie conſciences, and ſubdue our hard hearts into deep contrition. Pardon the many great offences of us thy ſervants, and the crying ſins of the whole Nation. Remove the evils we now lie under. Avert the judgments which we juſtly fear, becauſe we moſt juſtly deſerve. Diſcover more and more the ſnares of death. and Popiſh treachery, and let us never fall into the hands of thoſe men, whoſe mercies are cruel. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite all our hearts in the profeſſion of the true Religion, which thine own right hand hath planted amongſt us, and in a holy converſation an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable therete. Pour out thine abundant bleſſings upon our
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:56367:37"/>gracious King, and his great Council the preſent Parliament, Keep him as the apple of thine eye, hide him under the ſhadow of thy wings. Inform his Princes after thy will, and teach his Senators wiſdom: And grant that all their counſels, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions and endeavours may tend to, and end in the glory of thy great Name, the preſervation of the Church and true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion amongſt us, and the ſecurity, peace, and proſperity of theſe Kingdoms. All which we humbly beg in the Name, and through the Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt thy Son, our Saviour.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
